£­£½Subtitle Made By Qu Ya£½£­ www.qu.2ya.com
－＝瞿亚制作字幕＝－ www.qu.2ya.com
Freddy, go and find a cab.
弗雷迪, 去叫辆出租车
Do you want me to catch pneumonia?
你想害我得肺炎吗？
Don't just stand there, Freddy. Go and find a cab.
别干站着，弗雷迪，去叫辆出租车
All right, I'll get one.
好，我去叫
Look where you're goin', dear. Look where you're goin'!
小心看路，小心看路！
I'm so sorry.
真对不起
Two bunches o' violets trod in the mud. A full day's wages.
两束紫罗兰沾上泥，一天工钱全赔光了
-Freddy, go and find a cab. -Yes, Mother.
-弗雷迪，去叫辆出租车。-好，母亲
He's your son, is he?
他是你儿子，是吗？
If you'd done your duty as a mother should...
你可要尽做母亲的责任……
...you wouldn't let 'im spoil a poor girl's flow'rs and run away without payin'.
……你不能随他弄脏穷姑娘的花还不赔钱呀
Go about your business, my girl.
做你的买卖去，小姑娘
And you wouldn't go off without payin', either.
你可不能不赔钱就走
Two bunches o' violets trod in the mud.
两束紫罗兰沾上泥
Sir, is there any sign of it stopping?
先生，这雨会停吗？
I'm afraid not. It's worse than before.
恐怕不会，越下越大了
If it's worse, it's a sign it's nearly over.
越下越大的话，可能就快停了
Cheer up, Capt'n, buy a flow'r off a poor girl.
那好啊，长官，买一束穷姑娘的花吧
I'm sorry, I haven't any change.
对不起，我没有零钱
I can change 'alf a crown. Take this for tuppence.
我能找开半克朗。只要两便士
I told you, I'm awfully sorry. Wait a minute.
我说了没零钱，很抱歉。等等
Oh, yes. Here's three ha' pence, if that's any use to you.
嗯。这儿有三个小硬币，给你好了
Thank you, sir.
谢谢先生
You be careful. Better give 'im a flower for it.
小心点，拿了钱应该给他花
There's a bloke here behind that pillar...
柱子后面有个人…
...takin' down every blessed word you're sayin'.
…在记录你说的每句话
I ain't done nothin' wrong by speakin' to the gentleman.
我跟一位绅士说话有什么错
I've a right to sell flow'rs if I keep off the curb.
我有在街边卖花的权利
I'm a respectable girl, so help me.
我是正派人家的女儿，帮帮我
I never spoke to him except to ask him to buy a flow'r off me.
我只是求他买我的花
-What's the bloomin' noise? -A tec's takin' her down.
-怎么这么吵？-有个侦探盯着她
I'm makin' an honest livin'.
我没做过坏事
Who's doing all that shouting?
谁在大喊大叫？
Sir, don't let 'im charge me. You dunno what it means to me.
先生，别让他抓我，我害怕
They'll take away me character and drive me on the streets...
这会毁掉我的名誉让我流浪街头…
...for speakin' to gentlemen.
…罪名是跟绅士讲话
There, there. Who's hurting you, you silly girl? What'd you take me for?
喂，谁要抓你，傻姑娘？你当我是谁？
On my Bible oath, I never spoke a word.
我发誓我什么也没说
Shut up! Do I look like a policeman?
住嘴！我象个警察吗？
Why'd ya take down me words? 'Ow do I know you took me down right?
你干嘛记录我的话？谁知道你记得对不对？
You just show me what you wrote ab'ut me.
你让我看看你是怎么记的
That ain't proper writin'. I can't read it.
这字写得不对。我读不出
I can.
我读得出
'"l say, Capt'n, now buy a flow'r off a poor girl.'"
那好啊，长官，买一束穷姑娘的花吧
Oh, it's cause I called him '"Capt'n.'"
啊，就为我叫他“长官”
I meant no 'arm. Sir, don't let him lay a charge against me for a word like that.
我不是故意说错的，先生，别让他抓我
I'll make no charge. Really, sir, if you are a detective...
我不会让他抓你的。先生，如果你是侦探…
...you needn't protect me against molestation from young women...
…我想这姑娘没有骚扰我…
...until I ask you.
…不必麻烦你了
Anyone could tell the girl meant no harm.
谁都知道这姑娘没有恶意
He ain't no tec. He's a gentleman. Look at his boots.
他不是侦探。他是位绅士，瞧他的靴子
How are all your people down at Selsey?
你们是从赛西来的吧
Who told you my people come from Selsey?
是谁告诉你我们是从赛西来的？
Never mind, they do.
没猜错
How do you come to be up so far east? You were born in Lisson Grove.
你怎么会到这么远的这方来？你是利森林出生的吧
What 'arm is there in my leavin' Lisson Grove?
我不想在利森林住怎么啦？
It weren't fit for pigs to live. I had to pay four and six a week.
那地方象猪圈，花销又贵得要死
Live where you like but stop that noise!
随便你住哪里，可不要再发这噪声了！
Come, come, he can't touch you. You've a right to live where you please.
喂，他管不了你，你爱住哪里就住哪里
I'm a good girl, I am.
我可是正经人家的女儿
-Where do I come from? -Hawkestone.
-我从哪儿来？ -豪克斯通
Who said I didn't? Blimey, you know everything, you do.
一点不错！天，你真是什么都知道
You, sir, do you think you could find me a taxi?
喂，先生，你能帮我找辆出租车吗？
Madam, it's stopped raining.
女士，雨停了
You can get a motorbus to Hampton Court.
你可以乘公共汽车回汉普顿园
Isn't that where you live?
你是住在那儿吧？
What impertinence!
真没礼貌！
Tell 'im where he comes from, if you wanta go fortune-telling.
说说他是哪儿来的，算你真有本事
Cheltenham, Harrow...
切特纳姆，哈洛…
...Cambridge and...
…剑桥和…
...lndia?
…印度？
Quite right.
很正确
He ain't a tec, he's a bloomin' busybody.
他不是侦探，是个算命先生
Do you do this sort of thing for a living at a music hall?
你总在音乐厅前面算命为业吗？
I have thought of it. Perhaps I will one day.
我倒是可以考虑
He's no gentleman, he ain't, to interfere with a poor girl!
他才不是绅士，居然欺负一个穷姑娘
How do you do it, may I ask?
我能问问你究竟是怎么知道的吗？
Simple phonetics. The science of speech. That's my profession. Also my hobby.
通过语音，语言学，这是我的职业和爱好
Anyone can spot an lrishman or a Yorkshireman by his brogue...
谁都听得出爱尔兰或约克郡的口音
...but I can place a man within six miles.
…可我能能把地理范围准确到六里以内
I can place 'im within two miles in London. Sometimes within two streets.
伦敦人我能准确到两里，有时两条街道之间
Ought to be ashamed of 'imself, unmanly coward.
他该感到羞耻，真不是人
-Is there a living in that? -Oh, yes.
-靠这也能吃饭？ -对
Let him mind his own business and leave a poor girl alone.
叫他管好自己的事别再欺负一个穷姑娘
Cease this detestable boohooing instantly...
马上停止这剌耳的声音…
...or else seek the shelter of some other place of worship!
…要么躲到个没人的地方去！
I have a right to be here if I like, same as you!
我有权呆在这里，跟你一样！
A woman who utters such disgusting, depressing noises...
一个发着这么难听的噪音的女士…
...has no right to be anywhere, no right to live.
…没权利呆在任何地方，没权利活着
Remember, you're a human with a soul...
记住，你是个有灵魂的人类…
...and the divine gift of articulate speech.
…拥有语言的天赋
Your native language is the language of Shakespeare and...
你的母语是莎士比亚用的语言…
...Milton and the Bible. Don't sit there crooning like a bilious pigeon.
…弥尔顿和圣经的语言。别像鸽子样乱哼…
'"Look at her, a prisoner of the gutters
“为何挣扎在贫民窟里
'"Condemned by every syllable she utters
“只怪她那难听的发音
'"By right she should be taken out and hung
“按照语法该判她死罪
'"For the cold-blooded murder of the English tongue'"
“为对英语的冷血谋杀
Heavens, what a sound!
天哪，什么声音啊！
'"This is what the British population
“这就是大英民众
'"Calls an elementary education'"
“所谓的基础教育
Come, sir, I think you've picked a poor example.
喂，先生，我想你选择的样本不太恰当
Did l?
是吗？
'"Hear them down in Soho Square Dropping H's everywhere
“听听街头人们说话总省略‘H’
'"Speaking English any way they like
“由着性子胡说乱讲
'"Hey, you, sir, did you go to school?
“嗨，你，先生，你可是去学校？
'"What ya tike me for, a fool?
“你当我是啥，傻瓜？
'"No one taught him 'take' instead of 'tike'
“没人教过他该怎么发‘当’这个音
'"Hear a Yorkshireman, or worse Hear a Cornishman converse
“再听听约克郡还有康尼斯郡人说话
'"l'd rather hear a choir singing flat
“我宁可去听教堂唱诗班
'"Chickens cackling in a barn Just like this one
“一群鸡在谷仓咯咯叫”就象这个样
'"Garn!
“哼！
'"l ask you, sir, what sort of word is that?
“请问，先生，那是什么字？
'"lt's 'aoow' and 'garn' that keep her in her place
“就是‘呕’和‘哼’使她没前途
'"Not her wretched clothes and dirty face
“而不是因为他的破衣和脏脸
'"Why can't the English teach their children how to speak?
“为何英国人就不能教会孩子怎么说话？
'"This verbal class distinction by now should be antique
“凭发音区别阶级现在已过时
'"lf you spoke as she does, sir, instead of the way you do
“要是你也象她那样说话，先生
'"Why, you might be selling flowers, too'"
“你大概也只能卖花”
I beg your pardon.
对不起
'"An Englishman's way of speaking absolutely classifies him
“英国人的发音能分三六九等
'"The moment he talks he makes some other Englishman despise him
“发音不对别人会把你轻视
'"One common language I'm afraid we'll never get
“我们已经失去了共同语言
'"Oh, why can't the English learn to...
“唉，为何英国人不能
'"...set a good example to people whose English is painful to your ears
“…给说不好英语的人树立个好榜样
'"The Scotch and the lrish leave you close to tears
“苏格兰人和爱尔兰人开口能令你痛哭流涕
'"There even are places where English completely disappears
“许多地方英语甚至已经灭绝
'"Why, in America they haven't used it for years!
“美国人说的早就不再是英语！
'"Why can't the English teach their children how to speak?
“为何英国人就不能教会孩子怎么说话？
'"Norwegians learn Norwegian, the Greeks are taught their Greek
“挪威人会挪威语，希腊人会希腊语
'"ln France every Frenchman knows his language from 'A' to 'Z'
“在法国人人都精通法语
'"The French don't care what they do actually
“法国人不用关心如何讲话
'"As long as they pronounce it properly
“因为他们总能正确发音
'"Arabians learn Arabian with the speed of summer lightning
“阿拉伯人学阿拉伯语象闪电一样快
'"The Hebrews learn it backwards which is absolutely frightening
“希伯莱人能倒过来说希伯莱语
'"Use proper English, you're regarded as a freak
“说正确英语的，反而被当作怪人
'"Oh, why can't the English
“为何英国人就不能
'"Why can't the English learn to speak?'"
“为何英国人就不能教会孩子怎么说话？”
Thank you.
谢谢
See this creature with her curbstone English...
听听她讲的那破英语…
...that'll keep her in the gutter till the end of her days?
…她到死都只能呆在贫民窟
In six months I could pass her off as a duchess at an Embassy Ball.
六个月内我能使她像公爵夫人般参加使馆舞会
I could get her a job as a lady's maid or a shop assistant...
我能让她当上贵夫人的侍从或商铺店员…
...which requires better English.
…这些需要讲更好英语的工作
What's that you say?
你说什么？
Yes, you squashed cabbage leaf!
你象地上的烂菜叶！
You disgrace to the noble architecture of these columns!
你实在是有碍市容！
You incarnate insult to the English language!
你纯粹是在给英语抹黑！
I could pass you off as the Queen of Sheba.
但我能把你变成圣经里的示巴女王
You don't believe that, Capt'n?
你不相信吧，长官？
Anything's possible. I, myself, am a student of lndian dialects.
有可能。我自己也正在学印度方言
Are you? Do you know Colonel Pickering, the author of Spoken Sanskrit?
是吗？你认识皮克林上校吗，《梵文口语》的作者？
I am Colonel Pickering. Who are you?
我就是皮克林上校。你是哪位？
I'm Henry Higgins, author of Higgins' Universal Alphabet.
我是享利希金斯，《希氏通用字母表》的作者
I came from lndia to meet you!
我特地从印度来拜访你！
I was going to lndia to meet you!
我也打算到印度去拜访你！
-Where are you staying? -At the Carleton.
-你住哪里？ -查尔顿
No, you're not. You're staying at 27A Wimpole Street.
别住那里，到温坡街27A座来
You come with me. We'll have a little jaw over supper.
住我家里。我们在餐桌上好好聊聊
Indian dialects have always fascinated me.
对印度方言我一向很感兴趣
Buy a flower. I'm short for me lodgin'.
买束花吧。不然我房钱都付不起
Liar!
撒谎！
You said you could change half a crown.
你说过你能找开半克朗
You ought to be stuffed with nails, you ought!
你这天杀的！
Here, take the whole bloomin' basket for a sixpence!
整篮拿去，只要六便士！
A reminder.
做个纪念
-How many are there actually? -How many what?
-到底有多少种？ -多少种什么？
Indian dialects?
印度方言？
No fewer than 147 distinct languages are recorded as vernacular in lndia.
有记录的不少于147种
Shouldn't we stand up, gentlemen? We've got a bloomin' heiress in our midst.
我们站一下，先生们？这儿有位贵夫人
Would you be lookin' for a good butler, Eliza?
你想找个好管家吗，伊莱莎？
Well, you won't do.
嗯，你不行
'"lt's rather dull in town I think I'll take me to Paris
“城里真没劲，我得去趟巴黎
'"The missus wants to open up the castle in Capri
“女士们要到卡布利城堡
'"Me doctor recommends a quiet summer by the sea
“医生劝我到海边消夏
'"Wouldn't it be loverly?'"
“这难道不惬意？”
Where are ya bound for this year, Eliza? Biarritz?
今年你要去哪里，伊莱莎？去伯利兹？
'"All I want is a room somewhere
“我只要一个小房间
'"Far away from the cold night air
“隔开深夜的冷空气
'"With one enormous chair
“里面有把大躺椅
'"Oh, wouldn't it be loverly?
“这难道不惬意？
'"Lots of chocolate for me to eat
“许许多多的巧克力
'"Lots of coal makin' lots of 'eat
“炭火烧得暖洋洋
'"Warm face, warm 'ands, warm feet
“从头到脚都温暖
'"Oh, wouldn't it be loverly?
“这难道不惬意？
'"Oh, so loverly sittin'
“哦，舒舒服服地坐着
'"Absobloominlutely still
“安安静静地休息
'"l would never budge till Spring
“开春再出去
'"Crept over the winder sill
“靠着窗台晒太阳
'"Someone's 'ead restin' on my knee
“和他偎依在一起
'"Warm and tender as he can be
“温柔又甜蜜
'"Who takes good care of me
“永远保护我
'"Oh, wouldn't it be loverly?
“这难道不惬意？
'"Loverly
“惬意
'"All I want is a room somewhere
“我只要一个小房间
'"Far away from the cold night air
“隔开深夜的冷空气
'"With one enormous chair
“里面有把大躺椅
'"Oh, wouldn't it be loverly?
“这难道不惬意？
'"Lots of chocolate for me to eat
“许许多多的巧克力
'"Lots of coal makin' lots of 'eat
“炭火烧得暖洋洋
'"Warm face, warm 'ands, warm feet
“从头到脚都温暖
'"Oh, wouldn't it be loverly?
“这难道不惬意？
'"Oh, so loverly sittin'
“哦，舒舒服服地坐着
'"Absobloominlutely still
“安安静静地休息
'"l would never budge till Spring
“开春再出去
'"Crept over the winder sill
“靠着窗台晒太阳
'"Someone's 'ead restin' on my knee
“和他偎依在一起
'"Warm and tender as he can be
“温柔又甜蜜
'"Who takes good care of me
“永远保护我
'"Oh, wouldn't it be loverly?
“这难道不惬意？
'"Loverly
“惬意
'"Wouldn't it be loverly?'"
“这难道不惬意？
Come on, Alfie, let's go 'ome now. This place is givin' me the willies.
快，艾菲，咱们回去吧，这地方我不想呆了
Home? What do you want to go 'ome for?
回去？为什么想回去？
It's nearly 5:00. My daughter Eliza'll be along soon.
快五点了，我女儿伊莱莎快回来了
She ought to be good for 'alf a crown for a father that loves 'er.
希望她对得好老爸起为她花的半个克朗
That's a laugh. You ain't been near 'er for months.
真可笑，你好几个月没见她了
What's that got to do with it? What's 'alf a crown after all I've give 'er?
那又怎样，我不是给了她半个克朗？
When did you ever give 'er anythin'?
你给过她什么东西？
Anythin'? I give 'er everythin'.
什么东西？我什么东西都给了她
I give 'er the greatest gift any human being can give to another:
我给了一个人所能给予的最大礼物：
Life!
生命！
I introduced 'er to this here planet, I did, with all its wonders and marvels.
我带她来到这个神奇的星球
The sun that shines, the moon that glows.
阳光灿烂，月光如水
Hyde Park to walk through on a fine spring night.
春季的夜晚能在海德公园漫步
The 'ole ruddy city o' London to roam around in sellin' 'er bloomin' flow'rs.
能在繁华的伦敦街市卖鲜花
I give 'er all that.
这都是我给她的
Then I disappears and leaves 'er on 'er own to enjoy it.
然后我默默离开让她独享这一切
If that ain't worth 'alf a crown now and again...
要是这一切值不到半个克朗…
...l'll take my belt off and give 'er what for.
…我就抽出皮带让她好看
You got a good 'eart. But you want a 'alf a crown out o' Eliza...
你真是好心人，要伊莱莎交半个克朗…
...you better have a good story.
…你得有更好的理由
Leave that to me, my boy.
放心吧，小子
-Good mornin', George. -Not a brass farthin'.
-早上好，乔治。-一个铜板都没
Not a brass farthin'.
一个铜板都没
There she is.
她在那儿
Why, Liza, what a surprise.
伊莱莎，真想不到
Hop along, Charlie, you're too old for me.
一边凉快去，查理，你对我来说太老了
-Don't you know your daughter? -You don't know what she looks like.
-你不认识你女儿了？ -不记得她长什么么样子
I know 'er, I know 'er. Come on, I'll find 'er.
我知道，我知道，走吧，我会找到她的
Eliza, what a surprise.
伊莱莎，真想不到
Not a brass farthin'.
一个铜板都没
Hey, you come 'ere, Eliza.
你过来，伊莱莎
I ain't gonna take me 'ard-earned wages...
我辛苦挣来的钱…
...and let you pass 'em on to a bloody pubkeeper.
…你全拿去送给酒馆老板
You wouldn't send me 'ome to your stepmother...
你总不至于赶我去你继母那里…
...without a drop o' liquid protection, would ya?
…连口酒都不给我喝吧
Stepmother, indeed!
继母，哼！
Well, I'm willin' to marry 'er. It's me that suffers by it.
嗯，我宁可跟她结婚，承受痛苦
I'm a slave to that woman, Eliza.
现在我是简直是那女人的奴隶，伊莱莎
Just because I ain't 'er lawful 'usband.
就因为我不是她合法的丈夫
Come on.
别这样
Slip your ol' dad just 'alf a crown to go 'ome on.
给我半克朗我就走人
Well, I had a bit o' luck meself last night.
嗯，昨晚我运气还不错
But don't keep comin' around countin' on 'alf crowns from me!
但以后别再来跟我要钱了！
Thank you, Eliza. You're a noble daughter.
谢谢，伊莱莎。你真是个大孝女
'"Beer, beer, glorious beer
“啤酒，啤酒，伟大的啤酒
'"Fill yourself right up'"
“一个人好好灌个饱”
See this creature with her curbstone English...
听听她讲的那破英语…
...that will keep her in the gutter till the end of her days?
…她到死都只能呆在贫民窟
In six months, I could pass her off as a duchess at an Embassy Ball.
六个月内我能使她像女公爵般参加使馆舞会
I could get her ajob as a lady's maid or a shop assistant...
我能让她当上贵夫人的侍从或商铺店员…
...which requires better English.
…这些需要讲更好英语的工作
You disgrace to the noble architecture of these columns!
你实在是有碍市容！
I could get her ajob as a lady's maid or a shop assistant...
我能让她当上贵夫人的侍从或商铺店员…
...which requires better English.
…这些需要讲更好英语的工作
How many vowel sounds did you hear altogether?
你总共听出几种不同元音？
I believe I counted 24.
我想有24种
Wrong by 100. To be exact you heard 130.
差得远。只际上有130种
Listen to them one at a time.
再来听一遍
Must l? I'm really quite done up for one morning.
不必吧？我听了整一个上午了
Your name, please?
您贵姓？
Your name, miss?
您贵姓，小姐？
My name is of no concern to you whatsoever.
我姓什么与你无关
One moment, please.
请等一下
London is gettin' so dirty these days.
伦敦真是越来越脏了
I'm Mrs. Pearce, the housekeeper. Can I help you?
我是佩思太太，这儿的管家，您有什么事？
Good morning, missus. I'd like to see the professor, please.
早安，太太。我想见教授
Could you tell me what it's about?
您能告诉我有什么事吗？
It's business of a personal nature.
是有关个人的私事
One moment, please.
请稍等
-Mr. Higgins? -What is it, Mrs. Pearce?
-希金斯先生？ -什么事，佩思太太？
There's a young woman who wants to see you, sir.
有位年轻女士想见你，先生
A young woman?
年轻女士？
What does she want?
她有什么事？
She's quite a common girl, sir. Very common indeed.
是位普通的姑娘，先生，非常普通
I should've sent her away, only I thought...
我本来该叫她走的，但我想…
...you wanted her to talk into your machine.
…你也许希望记录她的声音
-Has she an interesting accent? -Simply ghastly.
-她的口音很特别吗？ -很难听
Good. Let's have her in. Show her in, Mrs. Pearce.
好，让她进来，让她进来，佩思太太
This is rather a bit of luck. I'll show you how I make records.
真是好运气，我来给你演示怎么记录
We'll set her talking, then I'll take her down first in Bell's Visible Speech...
我们让她讲话，记录到贝尔音图机上
...then in broad Romic. Then we'll get her on the phonograph...
…再转写成罗米克音标。然后用留声机录音…
...so you can turn her on when you want with the written transcript before you.
…这样可以和音标记录相对照
This is the young woman, sir.
就是这位女士，先生
Good mornin', my good man.
早安，先生。
Might I 'ave a word with you?
我能跟你说句话吗？
Oh, no. This is the girl I jotted down last night.
啊，不。这姑娘我已经昨天记录过了
She's no use. I got the records I want of the Lisson Grove lingo.
她没用处。利森林一带的方言我已弄清楚了
I won't waste another cylinder on that.
我可不想为她再浪费一个录音滚筒
Be off with you. I don't want you.
你快走吧。我用不着你
Don't be so saucy. You ain't 'eard what I come for yet.
别那么肯定。你还不知道我来干什么呢
Did you tell 'im I come in a taxi?
你有没告诉他我是乘出租车来的？
Nonsense. Do you think a gentleman like Mr. Higgins cares...
胡闹。象希金斯先生这样的绅士会关心…
...what you came in?
…你乘什么来吗？
Oh, we are proud.
噢，我们都很骄傲
He ain't above givin' lessons, not 'im. I 'eard 'im say so.
他不教课，我听他这么说的
I ain't come here to ask for any compliment...
我来不是要听客气话…
...and if my money's not good enough, I can go elsewhere.
…要是我的钱不够，我就去别处
Good enough for what?
不够什么？
Good enough for you.
够付你学费
Now you know, don't ya? I'm come to 'ave lessons.
你听明白了吗？我是来学习的
And to pay for 'em, too, make no mistake.
还会付学费，别搞错了
Well!
噢！
And what do you expect me to say?
你希望我会怎么说？
Well, if you was a gentleman, you might ask me to sit down, I think.
嗯，如果你真是个绅士，我想你该请我坐下
Don't I tell you I'm bringin' you business?
我不是说了要照顾你生意吗？
Should we ask this baggage to sit down...
我们该请这小东西坐下…
...or shall we just throw her out of the window?
…还是该把她从窗口扔出去呢？
I won't be called a baggage. Not when I've offered to pay like any lady.
我可不是东西。我是来付钱给你的女士
What do you want, my girl?
你想做什么，姑娘？
I want to be a lady in a flow'r shop...
我想做个花店女店员…
...'stead of sellin' at the corner of Tottenham Court Road.
…而不是在街角卖花
But they won't take me unless I can talk more genteel.
但他们不要，除非我说话好听
He said 'e could teach me.
他说他能教我
Well, 'ere I am ready to pay 'im.
嗯，我愿意付钱
Not asking any favor and he treats me as if I was dirt.
不要求其他，他却待我象尘土
I know what lessons cost as well as you do and I'm ready to pay.
我知道你的课程的收费，我愿意付钱
How much?
多少？
Now you're talkin'.
这下你肯谈了
I thought you'd come off it for a chance to get back...
我想你应该给我优惠一点…
...a bit of what you chucked at me last night.
…因为你昨晚那样对待我
You'd had a drop in, 'adn't you?
应该吧，是不是？
Sit down.
坐下
-If you're goin' t' make a compliment of it-- -Sit down!
-如果你客气一点… -坐下！
Sit down, girl. Do as you're told.
坐下，姑娘。照我说的做
What's your name?
你叫什么名字？
Eliza Doolittle.
伊莱莎杜利特
Won't you sit down, Miss Doolittle?
请坐好吗，杜利特小姐？
I don't mind if I do.
我当然乐意
How much do you propose to pay me for these lessons?
你打算为这课程付多少钱？
Oh, I know what's right.
嗯，我知道行情
My lady friend gets French lessons for 18 pence an hour...
我的朋友花18便士一小时去学法语…
...from a real French gentleman.
…由真正的法国绅士上课
You wouldn't have the face to ask me the same...
你总不好意思要一样的价钱…
...for teachin' me my own language as you would for French.
…只不过教我自己的母语
I won't give more than a shillin'. Take it or leave it.
我最多出一先令，要不要随你
Do you know, Pickering, if you think of a shilling...
知道吗，皮克林，如果你不把一先令…
...not as a simple shilling, but as a percentage of this girl's income...
…仅仅当作一先令，而是算这姑娘收入的百分比…
...it works out as fully equivalent of...
…那么大概相当于…
...60 or 70 pounds from a millionaire.
…一个百万富翁拿出六七十镑…
By George, it's enormous. It's the biggest offer I ever had.
老天，太多了。这是我收得最多的一次
Sixty pounds? What are you talkin' about? Where would I get 60 pounds?
60镑？你说什么？我哪来的60镑？
-I never offered you 60 pounds! -Hold your tongue!
-我从没说要付你60镑！ -闭嘴！
But I ain't got 60 pounds!
可我跟本没有60镑！
Don't cry, silly girl. Sit down. Nobody's going to touch your money.
别哭了，傻姑娘。坐下，没人要抢你的钱
Somebody'll touch you with a broomstick if you don't stop sniveling.
再乱叫我让人拿扫帚教训你
Sit down!
坐下！
Anybody'd think you was my father!
别人还以为你是我父亲！
If I decide to teach you, I'll be worse than two fathers to you.
如果我决定教你，我会比两个父亲更厉害
Here.
给你
What's this for?
干什么？
To wipe your eyes. To wipe any part of your face that feels moist.
擦你的眼睛。脸上湿了要用这个擦
Remember, that's your handkerchief and that's your sleeve.
记住，这是你的手帕，那是你的袖子
Don't confuse one with the other, if you want to become a lady in a shop.
两个别搞混了，要是你想当个女店员的话
It's no use to talk to her like that. She doesn't understand you.
这么讲没用的。她听不明白
Give the 'andkerchief to me. He give it to me, not to you!
把手帕给我。他把它给我了，不是给你！
Higgins, I'm interested.
希金斯，我很好奇
What about your boast...
你夸口说…
...you could pass her off as a duchess at the Embassy Ball?
…你能使她像公爵夫人般参加使馆舞会？
I'll say you're the greatest teacher alive if you do that.
如果你能做到我得说你将是世上最伟大的老师
I'll bet you all the expenses of the experiment that you can't do it.
我打赌你做不到，否则我付全部有关费用
I'll even pay for the lessons.
甚至学费也由我付
You're real good. Thank ye, Capt'n.
你真好。谢谢你，长官
It's almost irresistible.
真是难以拒绝
She's so deliciously low.
她这么卑微
So horribly dirty.
这个肮脏
I ain't dirty! I washed my face an' hands before I come, I did.
我可不脏！我来以前刚洗过脸和手，真的
I'll take it. I'll make a duchess of this draggle-tailed guttersnipe.
我接受。我会将这个邋遢姑娘变成公爵夫人
We'll start today. This moment. Take her away and clean her.
我们今天就开始。现在，带她去洗洗干净
Sandpaper, if it won't come off. Is there a fire in the kitchen?
实在洗不掉就用砂纸。厨房里有炉火吗？
Take her clothes off and burn them and order some new ones.
把他的衣服脱掉烧了，去买新的
Just wrap her in brown paper till they come.
新的买来前让她先披牛皮纸
You're no gentleman, you're not, to talk o' such things.
你不是个绅士，你怎能这样说话
I'm a good girl, I am.
我是个正派姑娘，真的
And I know what the likes of you are, I do.
我看得出你是什么人，真的
We want none of your slum prudery here, young woman.
我们不用你装正经，女士
You've got to learn to behave like a duchess.
你的目标是学做公爵夫人
Take her away, Mrs. Pearce. If she gives you any trouble, wallop her.
把他带走，佩思太太。不听话就修理她
I'll call the police, I will.
我会叫警察的，真的
I've got no place to put her.
我没地方安排她
Well, put her in the dustbin.
嗯，把她安排到储藏室
Come, Higgins, be reasonable.
希金斯，你要讲讲道理
You must be reasonable, Mr. Higgins, you must.
你必须理智一点，希金斯先生
You can't walk over everybody like this.
你不该这样作践别人
I?
我？
Walk over everybody?
作践别人？
My dear Mrs. Pearce, my dear Pickering, I had no intention of walking over anybody.
亲爱的佩思太太，亲爱的皮克林，我没想作践人
I merely suggested we should be kind to this poor girl.
我只是建议我们应该对这穷姑娘亲切一点
I didn't express myself clearly because I didn't wish to hurt her delicacy...
我不说清楚，因为我不想伤害她的感情…
...or yours.
…或是你们的感情
But, sir, you can't take a girl up like that...
可是，先生，你不能这样对待一个姑娘…
...as if you were picking up a pebble on the beach.
…就好象从海边随便捡来的石头
Why not?
为什么不？
Why not? But you don't know anything about her.
为什么不？你完全不了解她
What about her parents? She may be married.
她父母是谁？她可能已结婚了
Garn!
哼！
There. As the girl very properly says, '"garn! '"
看，这姑娘说了：“哼！”
Who'd marry me?
谁会和我结婚？
By George, Eliza...
我发誓，伊莱莎，等我教好了你…
...the streets will be strewn with the bodies of men...
…整条街将堆满男人的尸体…
...shooting themselves for your sake before I'm done with you.
…因为争着向你求婚决斗而死
I'm goin'.
我要走了
He's off his chump, he is. I don't want no balmies teachin' me.
他有神经病，真的。我不要这家伙教我
Mad? All right, Mrs. Pearce, don't order those new clothes.
神经病？好，佩思太太，别买新衣服了
-Throw her out. -Stop! I won't allow it.
-把她扔出去。 -不！我不能这样做
Go home to your parents, girl.
回你父母家去，姑娘
I ain't got no parents.
我没有父母
She ain't got no parents. What's the fuss?
她没有父母。真是一团糟
Nobody wants her. She's no use to anyone but me. Take her upstairs!
她没人要。除了我没人要她，带她上楼！
What's to become of her? ls she to be paid anything?
她怎么办？她的花费都要你付？
Do be sensible, sir.
理智一点，先生
What'd she do with money? She'll have food and clothes.
她要钱干嘛？有吃的穿的够了
She'll drink if you give her money.
你给她钱她会酗酒
You are a brute! It's a lie!
你这畜生！你骗人！
Nobody ever saw the sign o' liquor on me.
我从来都不喝酒
Sir, you're a gentleman. Don't let 'im speak to me like that!
先生，你是个绅士。别让他这样对待我！
Does it occur to you, Higgins, the girl has some feelings?
你有没想过，希金斯，这姑娘也有感情？
No, I don't think so. No feelings we need worry about.
不，我没想过，我们不用担心感情的事
Well, have you, Eliza?
嗯，你有吗，伊莱莎？
I got me feelings same as anyone else.
我和别人一样有感情
Mr. Higgins, I must know on what terms the girl is to be here.
希金斯先生，我想知道这姑娘凭什么留在这里
What'll become of her when you've finished teaching?
你教完她以后怎么办？
You must look ahead a little, sir.
你得看得远一点，先生
What'll become of her if we leave her in the gutter, Mrs. Pearce?
到时我们把她送回贫民区吗，佩思太太？
That's her own business, not yours, Mr. Higgins.
那是她自己的事，不是你的，希金斯先生
When I'm done, we'll throw her back.
我教完了我们就送她回去
Then it'll be her own business again. That'll be all right, won't it?
让她接着做她自己的事，没问题吧？
You've no feelin' 'eart in ya!
你没有良心！
You don't care for nothin' but yourself.
你除了自己什么都不关心
I've 'ad enough of this. I'm goin'!
我受够了，我要走了！
You ought to be ashamed of yourself!
你该为自己感到羞耻！
Have some chocolates, Eliza.
来块巧克力，伊莱莎
'Ow do I know what might be in 'em?
我怎么知道里面放了什么？
I've 'eard of girls bein' drugged by the likes o' you.
我听说有姑娘被象你这样的骗子下药
Pledge of good faith.
作为保证
I'll take one half.
我吃一半
And you take the other.
你吃另一半
You'll have boxes of them, barrels of them every day.
每天你能整盒地吃巧克力
You'll live on them, eh?
你可以拿它当饭吃，嗯？
I wouldn't 've ate it, only I'm too ladylike to take it out o' me mouth.
我并不想吃，只不过是因为客气才吃的
Think of it, Eliza. Think of chocolates, and taxis...
想想看，伊莱莎。巧克力，出租车…
...and gold and diamonds.
…黄金和钻石
I don't want no gold and no diamonds. I'm a good girl, I am.
我才不想要黄金和钻石，我是正派姑娘
Higgins, I really must interfere. Mrs. Pearce is quite right.
希金斯，我必须干预此事。佩思太太是对的
If this girl will put herself in your hands for six months...
如果这姑娘要在你这里呆6个月…
...for an experiment in teaching, she must understand thoroughly what she's doing.
…为了做教学试验，她应该完全了解她在做什么
You are to stay here for the next six months...
你要在这里呆6个月…
...learning how to speak beautifully like a lady in a florist shop.
…学习怎么象花店里的淑女一样美妙地说话
If you're good and do what you're told, you'll sleep in a proper bedroom...
如果你表现好，你会有自己的卧室…
...have lots to eat, money to buy chocolates and take rides in taxis.
…有很多吃的，有钱买巧克力，乘出租车出门
But if you are naughty and idle...
但如果你淘气偷懒…
...you'll sleep in the kitchen amongst the black beetles...
…你就得在厨房里跟蟑螂睡一起…
...and be walloped by Mrs. Pearce with a broomstick.
…要被佩思太太用扫帚打…
At the end of six months, you shall be taken to Buckingham Palace...
6个月后，你会被带到白金汉宫…
...in a carriage, beautifully dressed.
…坐着马车，穿得漂漂亮亮的
If the king finds out that you are not a lady...
如果被国王发现你不是个淑女…
...the police will take you to the Tower of London where your head will be cut off...
…警察就会把你送到伦敦塔上砍脑袋…
...as a warning to other presumptuous flower girls.
…警告其他想装淑女的卖花女
But if you are not found out, you shall have a present of...
如果你没被认出来，你会得到…
...seven and six to start life with as a lady in a shop.
…六七镑奖金并当上女店员
If you refuse this offer...
如果你拒绝这么好的条件…
...you will be the most ungrateful, wicked girl...
…你就是个最无情的坏姑娘…
...and the angels will weep for you!
…天使都要为你哭泣！
Are you satisfied, Pickering?
你满意了吧，皮克林？
I don't understand what you're talking about.
我不明白你在说什么
Could I put it more plainly or fairly, Mrs. Pearce?
要我再解释一遍吗，佩思太太？
Come with me.
跟我来
That's right. Bundle her off to the bathroom.
好吧，带她去浴室
You're a great bully, you are!
你欺负人！
I won't stay here if I don't like it. I won't let nobody wallop me!
我不高兴时我就走。我才不要别人打我！
Don't answer back, girl.
别顶嘴，姑娘
I've always been a good girl, I 'ave.
我一向是个正派姑娘
In six months...in three, if she has a good ear and a quick tongue...
6个月内…只要3个月，如果她耳聪目明…
...l'll take her anywhere and I'll pass her off as anything.
…我就可以带她去任何地方，扮作任何人
I'll make a queen of that barbarous wretch!
我能把这野姑娘变成王后！
I've never had a bath in me life. Not what you'd call a proper one.
我这辈子都没洗过澡，哪种澡都没洗过
You know you can't be a nice girl inside if you're dirty outside.
你外表脏的话，也不可能成为有内在美的好姑娘
I'll have to put you in here. This will be your bedroom.
我把你安排在这儿。这是你的卧室
I couldn't sleep in here, missus.
我不能睡这儿，太太
It's too good for the likes o' me.
这儿对我来说太好了点
I should be afraid to touch anythin'.
我碰都不敢碰
I ain't a duchess yet, you know.
我还不是公爵夫人呢
What's this? This where you wash clothes?
这是什么？你们洗衣服用的吗？
This is where we wash ourselves, Eliza. And where I'm going to wash you.
洗我们自己用的，伊莱莎。现在我要洗你
You expect me to get into that and wet meself all over?
你要我在里面弄得全身湿乎乎的？
Not me!
我不要！
I shall catch me death.
我会死掉的
Come along now.
过来
Take your clothes off.
把你的衣服脱掉
Come on, girl, do as you're told.
快点，姑娘，听话，把衣服脱掉
Here, come on. Help me take these--
快来，帮我来给她脱…
Take your hands off me!
把你的手拿开！
I'm a good girl, I am!
我是正派姑娘，真的！
It ain't right! It ain't decent!
这不行！这不象样！
Get your hands off me!
把你的手拿开！
I'm a good girl, I am!
我是正派姑娘！
Forgive the bluntness, but if I'm to be in this business...
请原谅我的直率，既然我也参预此事…
...l shall feel responsible for the girl.
…我应该对这姑娘负责
I hope it's clearly understood that no advantage is to be taken of her position.
我希望她不会给人占了便宜
What, that thing? Sacred, I assure you.
什么，那种事？老天，我保证
Come now, you know what I mean. This is no trifling matter.
你明白我的意思，这可不是小事情
Are you a man of good character where women are concerned?
在女性眼里你应该是个正派男人吧？
Have you ever met a man of good character where women are concerned?
你见过在女性眼里的正派男人吗？
Yes, very frequently.
对，经常见到
I haven't. The moment I let a woman make friends with me...
我没见过。当一个女人和我做朋友…
...she becomes jealous, exacting...
…她一定变得嫉妒、苛刻…
...suspicious and a damned nuisance.
…多疑而且极讨人嫌…
The moment that I make friends with a woman I become selfish and tyrannical.
当我和一个女人做朋友我也会变得自私专横
So here I am, a confirmed old bachelor and likely to remain so.
所以我宁可一直做个单身汉
Well, after all, Pickering....
毕竟啊，皮克林…
'"l'm an ordinary man
“我是个平凡的男人
'"Who desires nothing more
“从来都要求得不多
'"Than just an ordinary chance
“只想有个平凡的机会
'"To live exactly as he likes
“能过自己希望的生活
'"And do precisely what he wants
“能做他喜欢做的事情
'"An average man, am I
“我是个普通的男人
'"Of no eccentric whim
“没什么古怪的念头
'"Who likes to live his life
“只想过自己的生活
'"Free of strife
“能够永远与世无争
'"Doing whatever he thinks is best for him
“做他觉得合适的事
'"Oh, just an ordinary man
“只是个平凡的男人
'"But let a woman in your life
“可如果女人进入了你的生活
'"And your serenity is through
“平静时光就此结束
'"She'll redecorate your home From the cellar to the dome
“她会把你的房子彻底地重修
'"Then go on to the enthralling fun of overhauling you!
“然后会彻底修理你！
'"Let a woman in your life
“让女人进入你的生活
'"And you are up against a wall
“你就象面对一道高墙
'"Make a plan and you will find She has something else in mind
“她心里想的可不一样
'"So rather than do either You do something else that neither
“你只好去做自己根本
'"Likes at all!
“不喜欢做的事！
'"You want to talk of Keats or Milton
“你想谈济慈和弥尔顿
'"She only wants to talk of love
“他想谈的却只有爱情
'"You go to see a play or ballet
“你想去看话剧或芭蕾
'"And spend it searching for her glove
“结果整晚替她找手套
'"Let a woman in your life
“让女人进入你的生活
'"And you invite eternal strife
“等于是去自找麻烦受
'"Let them buy their wedding bands
“让别人去为婚礼付钱
'"For those anxious little hands
“让别人手牵手进教堂
'"l'd be equally as willing For a dentist to be drilling
“我宁可找牙医看牙齿
'"Than to ever let a woman in my life!
“也不让女人进入我的生活！
'"l'm a very gentle man
“我是个很温和的男人
'"Even-tempered and good-natured Whom you never hear complain
“沉着冷静天性善良无人抱怨
'"Who has the milk of human kindness By the quart in every vein
“全身都透着亲切和气
'"A patient man am I Down to my fingertips
“从头到脚充满了耐心
'"The sort who never could Ever would
“这样的人永远都不会
'"Let an insulting remark escape his lips
“轻易对他人出言冒犯
'"A very gentle man
“一个非常温和的男人
'"But let a woman in your life
“可要让女人进入你的生活
'"And patience hasn't got a chance
“忍耐是不可能做的事
'"She will beg you for advice Your reply will be concise
“她虽然征求你的意见
'"And she'll listen very nicely
“装做认真倾听的样子
'"Then go out and do precisely What she wants!
“回头却自己乱做一气！
'"You were a man of grace and polish
“你曾经是文雅的男人
'"Who never spoke above a hush
“从不粗声大气打扰人
'"Now all at once you're using language
“现在你突然会乱骂人
'"That would make a sailor blush
“连水手听了都会脸红
'"Let a woman in your life
“让女人进入你的生活
'"And you're plunging in a knife!
“就像拿刀子刺你自己
'"Let the others of my sex
“让我们其他的男同胞
'"Tie the knot around their necks
“打起领结去教堂结婚
'"l'd prefer a new edition Of the Spanish lnquisition
“我宁可看新版西班牙语法书
'"Than to ever let a woman in my life
“也不要让女人进入我的生活
'"l'm a quiet-living man
“我是生活安定的男人
'"Who prefers to spend the evenings
“照我的方式度过夜晚
'"ln the silence of his room
“享受自己房间的宁静
'"Who likes an atmosphere as restful
“最喜欢那安祥的气氛
'"As an undiscovered tomb
“就象没人打扰的墓地
'"A pensive man am I Of philosophic joys
“我是喜欢沉思的男人
'"Who likes to meditate, contemplate
“享受凝神冥想的乐趣
'"Free from humanity's mad, inhuman noise
“远离凡世嘈杂的声响
'"A quiet-living man
“一个生活安定的男人
'"But let a woman in your life
“但让女人进入你生活
'"And your sabbatical is through
“你就永无安宁的日子
'"ln a line that never ends Come an army of her friends
“她的朋友象千军万马
'"Come to jabber and to chatter And to tell her
“在她的耳边叽叽喳喳
'"What the matter is with you!
“谈论着你的家长里短
'"She'll have a booming, boisterous family
“她会有个吵闹的家族
'"Who will descend on you en masse
“成群结队拥到你面前
'"She'll have a large, Wagnerian mother
“她妈妈嗓门象瓦格纳
'"With a voice that shatters glass!
“说话声音能震碎玻璃！
'"Let a woman in your life
“让女人进入你的生活
'"l shall never let a woman...
“我永远都不会让女人…
'"...in my life! '"
“进入我的生活！”
Get out of 'ere. Jamie, you get out, too!
滚出去。杰米，你也滚出去！
Come on, Doolittle. And remember, drinks is to be paid for or not drunk.
杜利特。喝酒要付钱，否则别喝那么多
Thanks for your 'ospitality, George.
谢谢你的款待，乔治
Send the bill to Buckingham Palace.
把帐单送到白金汉宫吧
Well, Alfie, there's nothin' else to do. I guess it's back to work.
嗯，阿非，没什么事了，回去干活吧
Work! Don't you dare mention that word in my presence again.
干活！在我面前少提这个
Look at all these poor blighters down here.
你瞧这些干活的穷光蛋
I used to do that sort of thing once. Just for exercise.
我以前干活只是为运动一下
It's not worth it. Takes up your whole day.
一点不值得，白费时间
Don't worry, boys. We'll get outta this somehow.
别担心，小子们
How do you think you'll do that?
你准备怎么做？
How? Same as always.
怎么做？跟以前一样
Faith, hope and a little bit o' luck.
信心、希望再加上一点好运
'"The Lord above gave man an arm of iron
“神给男人钢铁的臂膀
'"So he could do his job and never shirk
“他能忙碌工作不疲倦
'"With a little bit o' luck With a little bit o' luck
“但只要一点好运，只要一点好运
'"Someone else'll do the blinkin' work!
“别人会代替你去工作
'"With a little bit
“只要有一点
'"With a little bit o' luck You'll never work
“只要有一点好运你就不用工作
'"The Lord above made liquor for temptation
“是神造了诱人的美酒
'"To see if man could turn away from sin
“看看人能否远离诱惑
'"With a little bit o' luck With a little bit o' luck
只要有一点好运，只要有一点好运
'"When temptation comes you'll give right in.
“诱惑来时你马上屈服
'"With a little bit
“只要有一点
'"With a little bit o' luck You'll give right in.
“只要有一点好运你就马上屈服
'"Oh, you can walk the straight and narrow
“你可以慢慢地走小路
'"But with a little bit o' luck you'll run amuck!
“只要有一点好运你就横冲直撞！
'"The gentle sex was made for man to marry
“神造女性来诱人结婚
'"To share his nest and see his food is cooked
“双栖双宿又送来食物
'"With a little bit o' luck With a little bit o' luck
“只要有一点好运，只要有一点好运
'"You can have it all and not get hooked.
“你就能同样享受却不受婚姻枷锁
'"With a little bit
“只要有一点
'"With a little bit o' luck You won't get hooked
“只要有一点好运你就不受婚姻枷锁
'"With a little bit o' bloomin' luck!
“只要有一点通天好运！
'"They're always throwing goodness at you
“人们总会扔给你好东西
'"But with a little bit o' luck a man can duck
“只要有一点好运就可以躲开
'"The Lord above made man to 'elp his neighbor
“神造男人来帮助邻居
'"No matter where on land, or sea, or foam
“不管在地面海上或天空
'"With a little bit o' luck With a little bit o' luck
“只要有一点好运，只要有一点好运
'"When he comes around you won't be home'"
“邻居找来你就不在家
You'd make a good suffragette, Alfie.
你可以领导女权运动了，阿非
Why, there's the lucky man now.
啊，那个幸运儿来了
The Honorable Alfie Doolittle.
可敬的阿非杜利特
What are you doing in Eliza's house?
你在伊莱莎的屋里做什么？
Her former residence!
她的旧住处！
You can buy your own drinks now, Alfie Doolittle.
你现在得自己买酒喝了，阿非杜利特
Fallen into a tub of butter, you have.
你真是老鼠掉油缸里了
What are you talkin' about?
你说什么？
Your daughter, Eliza.
你的女儿，伊莱莎
You're a lucky man, Alfie Doolittle.
你走运了，阿非杜利特
What about Eliza?
伊莱莎怎么了？
He don't know. Her own father an' he don't know.
他还不知道。她的亲爹还不知道
Moved in with a swell, Eliza has.
伊莱莎回来光风过一次
Left here in a taxi all by herself, smart as paint.
又自己坐出租车走了
An' ain't been home for three days.
已经三天没回家了
Go on.
说下去
And this mornin' I gets a message from 'er.
今天早上我收到她的口信
She wants her things sent over...
她要我把她的东西…
...to 27A Wimpole Street...
…送到温坡街27A号…
...care of Professor Higgins.
…希金斯教授转交…
An' what things does she want?
她要的是什么东西？
Her birdcage and her Chinese fan.
她的鸟笼和中国折扇
But she says:
她还说：
'"Never mind about sending any clothes.'"
“为必送什么衣服来了”
I knew she had a career in front of 'er.
我早知道她前途无量
We're in for a booze-up.
我们得一起庆祝一下
The sun is shining on Alfred P. Doolittle.
这回阿非杜特利可走运了
'"A man was made to 'elp support his children
“神造男人来供养儿女
'"Which is the right and proper thing to do
“那是天经地义的事情
'"With a little bit o' luck With a little bit o' luck
“只要有一点好运，只要有一点好运
'"They'll go out and start supportin' you
“他们会反过来供养你
'"With a little bit
“只要有一点
'"With a little bit o' luck they'll work for you
“只要有一点好运他们就会替你工作
'"With a little bit o' bloomin' luck!
“只要有一点通天好运！
'"lt's a crime for a man to go philanderin'
“男人风流是项罪过
'"And fill his wife's poor 'eart with grief and doubt
“他妻子会伤心绝望
'"With a little bit o' luck With a little bit o' luck
“只要有一点好运，只要有一点好运
'"You can see the bloodhounds don't find out!
“她的狗鼻子就不会闻到！
'"With a little bit
“只要有一点
'"With a little bit o' luck She won't find out!
“只要有一点好运她就不会发现！
'"With a little bit o' bloomin' luck! '"
“只要有一点通天好运!”
The mail, sir.
邮件，先生
Pay the bills and say no to the invitations.
是帐单就付掉，是邀请函就推辞
You simply cannot go on working the girl this way.
你不能继续这样训练那姑娘
Making her say her alphabet over and over...
让她翻来覆去念字母表…
...from sunup to sundown, even during meals.
…从早到晚，吃饭时都不停
You'll exhaust yourself. When will it stop?
你都会累坏了，到什么时候是个头？
When she does it properly, of course. Is that all, Mrs. Pearce?
当然是到她念对的时候。还有事吗，佩思太太？
There's another letter from the American millionaire, Ezra D. Wallingford.
那个美国富翁伊兹拉威林福又有信寄来
He still wants you for his Moral Reform League.
还是想请你帮他办道德重整协会
Throw it away.
把信扔掉
It's the third letter he's written you. You should at least answer it.
这是他写来的第三封信了，起码你要回一封
All right, leave it on the desk, Mrs. Pearce. I'll try and get to it.
好吧，把它放桌子上，佩斯太太。我会看的
If you please, sir. There's a dustman downstairs, Alfred P. Doolittle...
先生。楼下来了个清洁工，叫阿非杜利特…
...who wants to see you. He says you have his daughter here.
…他想见你。他说她女儿在你这儿
I say!
我早说了！
Well, send the blackguard up.
嗯，叫那个流氓上来
He may not be a blackguard, Higgins.
他可能不是个流氓，希金斯
Nonsense. Of course he's a blackguard, Pickering.
胡说，他当然是个流氓，皮克林
I'm afraid we'll have some trouble with him.
我担心他会来找我们麻烦
No, I think not. Any trouble to be had, he'll have it with me. Not I with him.
不，不会。有麻烦也是我找他，不是他找我
Doolittle, sir.
杜利特，先生
-Professor Higgins? -Here!
-希金斯教授？ -在这儿！
Where?
哪儿？
Good morning, Governor.
早上好，大人
I come about a very serious matter, Governor.
我要是有要事相商，大人
Brought up in Houndslow.
在汉斯罗长大
Mother Welsh, I should think.
母亲是威尔士人，我想
What is it you want, Doolittle?
你想要什么，杜利特？
I want my daughter, that's what I want. See?
我想要我女儿，就是这样，明白了？
Of course you do. You're her father, aren't you?
当然了。你是她父亲，是吗？
I'm glad to see you have a spark of family feeling left.
我很高兴你还剩了一点人情味
She's in there. Yes, take her away at once.
她在这儿。好，马上带她走吧
What?
什么？
Take her away. Do you think I am going to keep your daughter for you?
带她走。你以为我会老替你养女儿吗？
Now, is this reasonable, Governor?
这么说讲理吗，大人？
Is it fairity to take advantage of a man like that?
这样占别人便宜公平吗？
The girl belongs to me. You got 'er. Where do I come in?
那姑娘是我的。现在你占了去，我怎么办？
How dare you come here and attempt to blackmail me!
你怎么敢到这儿来勒索我！
You sent her here on purpose!
你故意送她到这儿来的！
Don't take a man up like that, Governor.
别对我乱讲，大人
The police shall take you up. This is a plan...
警察会来收拾你。这是个阴谋…
...a plot to extort money by threats.
…敲诈钱财的阴谋…
I shall telephone the police.
我要打电话报警
Have I asked you for a brass farthin'?
我向你要过一个铜板吗？
I leave it to this gentleman 'ere. Have I said a word about money?
我让这位绅士评评理。我提到钱了吗？
Well, what else did you come for?
嗯，那你来是要什么？
What would a bloke come for?
我来能要什么？
Be 'uman, Governor.
讲点道理，大人
Alfred, you sent her here on purpose.
阿非，你故意送她来这儿的
So help me, Governor, I never did.
帮帮忙，大人，我根本没有
How did you know she was here?
那你怎么知道她在这儿？
I'd tell you, Governor, if you'd let me get a word in.
我会告诉你的，大人，如果你肯让我说
I'm willing to tell ya. I'm wanting to tell ya.
我愿意告诉你，我正想告诉你
I'm waiting to tell ya!
我急于告诉你！
You know, Pickering, this chap's got a certain natural gift of rhetoric.
你瞧，皮克林，这家伙确实有点修辞天赋
Observe the rhythm of his native woodnotes wild.
注意他说话的原始野性的节奏
'"l'm willing to tell you. I'm wanting to tell you. I'm waiting to tell you.'"
“我愿意告诉你，我正想告诉你，我急于告诉你”
That's the Welsh strain in 'im.
这是标准威尔士腔
How did you know Eliza was here if you didn't send 'er?
如果不是你送她来，你怎么知道她在这儿？
Well, she sent back for her luggage and I got to 'ear about it.
嗯，她叫人拿她的行李，我正好听说
She said she didn't want no clothes.
她还说不必送衣服给她了
What was I to think from that, Governor? I ask you, as a parent, what was I to think?
我会怎么想，大人？你说作为父亲我会怎么想？
So you came here to rescue her from worse than death, eh?
所以你来救她逃出火坑，是吗？
-Yes, sir, Governor. That's right. -Yes.
-对，先生，大人，没错。 -好
Mrs. Pearce!
佩思太太！
Eliza's father has come to take her away. Give her to him, will you?
伊莱莎的父亲来带她回去。你给他好吗？
Now wait a minute, Governor. Wait a minute.
等等，大人，等等
You and me is men o' the world, ain't we?
你我都是世间的凡人，对吧？
Men of the world, are we? Perhaps you'd better go, Mrs. Pearce.
世间的凡人，对吧？那你还是走吧，佩思太太
I think so indeed, sir!
好的，先生！
Here, Governor.
这样吧，大人
I've took a sort of a fancy to you and...
我对你印象很不错…
...if you want the girl, I ain't so set on 'avin' her home again...
…如果你要这姑娘，我就不坚持带她回去了…
...but what I might be open to is an arrangement.
…但我得打开天窗说亮话
All I ask is my rights as a father.
我要求作为一个父亲所具有的权利
You're the last man alive to expect me to let her go for nothing.
你也不希望我什么好处也没有就让她走吧
I can see you're a straight sort, Governor.
我看得出你是个正直的人，大人
So...
所以…
...what's a five pound note to you? An' what's Eliza to me?
…伊莱莎对你的价值比得上5镑对我的价值吧？
I think you should know, Doolittle...
我想你应该知道，杜利特…
...that Mr. Higgins' intentions are entirely honorable.
…希金斯的并没有不好的意图
Of course they are, Governor. If I thought they wasn't, I'd ask 50.
当然，大人。否则的话我会要50镑
You mean, you'd sell your daughter for 50 pounds?
你是说你愿用50镑换你的女儿？
Have you no morals, man?
你不感到不道德吗？
No, I can't afford 'em, Governor. Neither could you if you was as poor as me.
我买不起道德，大人，你象我一样穷也会这样
Not that I mean any 'arm, but...
我不想出口伤人，但…
...if Eliza is gonna have a bit out o' this, why not me, too?
…如果伊莱莎能从中得到好处，我为什么不？…
Why not?
为什么不？
Look at it my way. What am l?
站在我的角度看看，我是什么？
I ask ya, what am l? I'm one o' the undeserving poor, that's what I am.
我问你，我是什么？我只是个不必救济的穷人
Think what that means to a man.
想想这对一个男人意味着什么
It means he's up against middle-class morality for all the time.
这意味着他会看不起中产阶级的所谓道德
If there's anything goin' an' I ask for a bit of it, it's always the same story:
不管发生什么，我如果想要点好处，结果都一样：
'"You're undeservin', so you can't have it.'"
“你不必救济，所以不能给你”
But my needs is as great as the most deservin' widows that ever got money...
但我和穷寡妇一样需要钱…
...out of six different charities in one week for the death o' the same 'usband.
…她们可以因死一个老公向六个慈善团拿六份救济
I don't need less than a deservin' man, I need more.
我需要的不比该救济的人少，反而更多
I don't eat less 'earty than he does and I drink...
我吃得不比他少，而且要喝点…
...a lot more.
…喝得挺多
I'm playin' straight with you.
我坦白跟你说
I ain't pretendin' to be deservin'. No, I'm undeservin'...
我不是装穷要救济。我不必救济…
...and I mean to go on bein' undeservin'. I like it an' that's the truth.
…我可以不用救济过活，但确实乐意有救济
But will you take advantage of...
你总不好意思…
a man's nature...
占人便宜
...do him out of the price of his own daughter, what he's brought up...
…让他和他的女儿骨肉分离…
...fed and clothed by the sweat of his brow...
…他辛辛苦苦将她养大…
...till she's growed big enough to be interestin' to you two gentlemen?
…出落得你们这两位绅士都感兴趣？
Is five pounds unreasonable, I put it to you?
5镑还不合理吗，你们想想看吧？
And I leave it to you.
你们看着办吧
You know, Pickering, if we took this man in hand for three months...
知道吗，皮克林，如果我训练这个人三个月…
...he could choose between a seat in the Cabinet and a popular pulpit in Wales.
…他就可以进内阁或做闻名威尔士的布道师
-We'd better give 'im a fiver. -He'll make bad use of it, I'm afraid.
-我们最好给他5镑钱。 -我担心他会乱花
Not me, Governor, so 'elp me I won't.
不会，大人，我不会的
Just one good spree for meself an' the missus...
我就和我女友喝点酒…
...givin' pleasure to ourselves and employment to others.
…增加生活情趣，也给别人找点活干
An' satisfaction to you to know it ain't been throwed away.
你会满意钱没有被浪费的
You couldn't spend it better.
这钱你来用也是一样
This is irresistible. Let's give 'im ten.
真是难以拒绝，我们给他10镑好了
The missus wouldn't have the 'eart to spend ten.
我女友花不了10镑钱
Ten pounds is a lot o' money.
10镑太多了
Makes a man feel prudent-like, and then goodbye to 'appiness.
会让人变得小心谨慎，从此不快乐
No, you just give me what I ask, Governor. Not a penny less, not a penny more.
你只需给5镑，大人。不要多也不要少
I rather draw the line at encouraging this sort of immorality.
我得干预一下这种不太道德的事
Why don't you marry that missus of yours?
你为何不和你女友结婚？
After all, marriage isn't so frightening. You married Eliza's mother.
结婚没这么可怕吧。你和伊莱莎母亲结过婚吧
Who told you that, Governor?
谁告诉你的，大人？
Well, nobody told me. I concluded, naturally....
没人告诉我，我推想理应如此…
If we listen to this man for another minute we'll have no convictions left.
如果听这人说下去，我们不会再有信心推理了
-Five pounds, I think you said. -Thank you, Governor.
-5镑，是吧。 -谢谢，大人
Are you sure you won't have ten?
你确定不想要10镑？
No. No, perhaps another time.
不，不，也许以后吧
I beg your pardon, miss.
对不起，小姐
I won't say those ruddy vowels one more time.
我再也不想念这些该死的元音了
Blimey, it's Eliza.
啊，伊莱莎
I never thought she'd clean up so good-looking.
我没想到她会变这么漂亮
She does me credit, don't she?
她真是给我争光，是吧？
What are you doin' here?
你来干什么？
Now, you hold your tongue and don't you give these gentlemen none o' your lip.
你不要说话，别让这两位绅士笑话
If you have any trouble with 'er, give 'er a few licks o' the strap.
如果她给你找麻烦，用皮带抽
That's the way to improve 'er mind.
这样她会乖起来的
Well, good morning, gentlemen. Cheerio, Eliza.
嗯，早安，绅士们。好样的，伊莱莎
There's a man for you. A philosophical genius of the first water.
就是这个人。一位哲学天才
Write to Mr. Ezra Wallingford and tell him...
给伊兹拉威林福写信告诉他…
...if he wants a lecturer, to get in touch with Mr. Doolittle...
…如果他需要演说家，就去找杜利特先生…
...a common dustman, one of the most original moralists in England.
…一位普通清洁工，全英国道德观最原始的人
What did he come for?
他来干嘛？
Say your vowels.
念你的元音去
I know me vowels. I knew 'em before I come.
我会念元音。我来之前就会了
If you know them, say them.
如果你会了，那就说说看
Ahyee, e, iyee, ow, you.
Ahyee, e, iyee, ow, you.
A, E, l, O, U.
A, E, I, O, U.
That's what I said. Ahyee, e, iyee, ow, you.
我就是这么念的。
That's what I've said for three days an' I won't no more.
我这么念了三天了，再也不想念了
I know it's difficult, Miss Doolittle, but try to understand.
我知道这很难，杜利特小姐，但请理解
There's no use explaining. As a military man you should know that.
解释是没用的。作为军人你该知道
Drilling is what she needs.
她需要的是训练
Leave her alone or she'll turn to you for sympathy.
别理她，否则她会向你骗同情
Very well, if you insist, but have a little patience with her.
好吧，如果你坚持，但请对她有点耐心
Of course.
当然
Say '"A.'"
说“A”
You ain't got no 'eart, you ain't.
你真是没良心
I promise you, you'll say your vowels correctly before this day is out...
我告诉你，今天你一定要把元音念正确…
...or there'll be no lunch, no dinner, and no chocolates.
…否则没有午餐，没有晚餐，没有巧克力
'"Just you wait, 'Enry 'lggins Just you wait
“等着瞧，亨利希金斯，等着瞧
'"You'll be sorry But your tears will be too late
“你会伤心失望，流下悔恨的眼泪
'"You'll be broke and I'll have money Will I help you? Don't be funny!
“你破产时要我出钱帮你？想得美！
'"Just you wait, 'Enry 'lggins Just you wait
“等着瞧，亨利希金斯，等着瞧
Till you're sick
“等着瞧，亨利希金斯，等你得了病
'"And you screams To fetch a doctor double-quick
“大喊大叫着要我去请医生
'"l'll be off a second later And go straight to the theater
“我会立刻出发直接上戏院
'"Ho, ho, ho, 'Enry 'lggins Just you wait!
“哈哈哈，亨利希金斯，等着瞧！
'"Just you wait Until we're swimmin' in the sea
“等着瞧，等我们去海里游泳
'"And you get the cramp a little ways from me
“你忽然在我不远处抽了筋
'"When you yell you're gonna drown I'll get dressed and go to town
“你淹死前大叫救命，我穿好衣服回城里
'"Just you wait!
“等着瞧！
'"One day I'll be famous I'll be proper and prim
“有一天我出了名，高贵又斯文
'"Go to St. James so often I will call it St. Jim
“三天两头去国家大教堂
'"One evening the king will say 'Oh, Liza, old thing
“一天晚上国王会说：‘伊莱莎，爱卿
'"'l want all of England your praises to sing
“我要将你的事迹在全国传扬
'"'Next week on the 20th of May
“下星期5月20日
'"'l proclaim Liza Doolittle Day
“‘我宣布为伊莱莎杜利特节
'"'All the people will celebrate the glory of you
“‘所有人会为庆祝你的荣耀
'"'And whatever you wish and want I gladly will do'
“‘不论你要什么我都答应你’
'"'Thanks a lot, King,' says I in a manner well-bred
“‘多谢国王’我彬彬有礼地回答说
'"'But all I want is 'Enry 'lggins' 'ead'
“‘我只想要亨利希金斯的人头’
'"'Done!'
“‘好！’
'"Says the king with a stroke
“国王当扬拍板
'"'Guard, run and bring in the bloke'
“‘卫兵，快去把那家伙带来’
'"Then they'll march you, 'Enry 'lggins, to the wall
“他们就押着你，亨利希金斯上刑场
'"And the king will tell me:
“国王会对我说：
'"'Liza, sound the call'
“‘伊莱莎，你来下令’
'"As they raise their rifles higher
“他们高举起步枪
'"l'll shout: 'Ready, aim, fire!'
“我会高喊：‘准备，瞄准，开火！’
'"Ho, ho, ho, 'Enry 'lggins, down you go
“哈哈哈，亨利希金斯，去死吧
'"Just you wait! '"
“等着瞧！”
All right, Eliza, say it again.
好了，伊莱莎，再念一遍
'"The rine in Spine...
“西班牙的雨…
'"...stais minely in the pline.'"
“都下在平原”
'"The rain in Spain stays mainly in the plain.'"
“西班牙的雨都下在平原”
Didn't I saiy that?
我不是这么说的吗？
No, Eliza, you didn't '"saiy'" that. You didn't even '"say'" that.
不，伊莱莎，你没这么说，你根本没说对
Every night before you go to bed, where you used to say your prayers...
每晚你睡觉前，原来做祷告的时间…
...l want you to say:
…我要你拿来念：
'"The rain in Spain stays mainly in the plain.'"
“西班牙的雨都落在平原”
Fifty times.
五十遍
You'll get much further with the Lord if you learn not to offend His ears.
说对了才不会冒犯神的耳朵
Now for your '"H's.'"
现在你练习“H”的发音
Pickering, this is going to be ghastly.
皮克林，真是急死人了
Control yourself, Higgins. Give the girl a chance.
冷静点，希金斯。给这姑娘一个机会
I suppose you can't expect her to get it right the first time.
我想你不该指望她第一次就说对
Come here, Eliza, and watch closely.
过来，伊莱莎，看仔细
Now, you see that flame?
你看看见火焰没有？
Every time you pronounce the letter '"H'" correctly the flame will waver...
如果你念对了“H”的发音火焰就会晃动…
...and every time you drop your '"H'" the flame will remain stationary.
…如果没发出“H”火焰就不会动
That's how to know you've done it correctly.
这样你就知道你有没有念对了
In time, your ear will hear the difference.
时间长了，你的耳朵就会听出区别
You'll see it better in the mirror. Now listen carefully.
你可以在镜子里看清楚。现在听仔细
'"ln Hartford, Hereford and Hampshire...
“在哈特福德、赫福德和汉普郡…
'"...hurricanes hardly ever happen.'"
“…从不刮飓风”
Now you repeat that after me.
现在你跟我念一遍
'"ln Hartford, Hereford and Hampshire, hurricanes hardly ever happen.'"
“在哈特福德、赫福德和汉普郡从不刮飓风”
Oh, no, no!
不，不！
Have you no ear at all?
你没有耳朵吗？
-Should I do it over? -No, please.
-我再念一遍？ -不用
Start from the very beginning. Just do this.
还是从头开始。这样好了
Go on, go on.
继续，继续
Does the same thing hold true in lndia?
在印度是不是也这样？
Have they the peculiar habit of not only dropping a letter...
他们是不是也省略某个字母的发音…
...but using it where it doesn't belong, like '"hever'" instead of '"ever'"?
…没这音的词偏又加上，就象不说ever说hever？
The girl, Higgins!
那姑娘，希金斯！
Go on. Go on.
继续，继续
''Poor Professor Higgins
“可怜的希金斯教授
'"Night and day he slaves away
“从早到晚埋头苦干
'"All day long on his feet
“整日整夜不停奔忙
'"Up and down until he's numb
“跑上跑下腿脚麻木
'"Doesn't rest, doesn't eat
“不休息，不吃饭
'"Doesn't touch a crumb'"
“不沾一片面包屑
Again, Eliza.
再来，伊莱莎
How kind of you to let me come.
你让我来真是太好了
No. '"Kind of you.'"
No. '"Kind of you.'"
Kind of you. It's like '"cup of tea.'"
Kind of you. It's like '"cup of tea.'"
Kind of you. Cup of tea. Say, '"cup of tea.'"
Kind of you. Cup of tea. Say, '"cup of tea.'"
Cuppatea.
Cuppatea.
No. '"A cup of tea.'"
No. '"A cup of tea.'"
It's awfully good cake. I wonder where Mrs. Pearce gets it.
这点心真好吃。佩思太太哪买来的
First rate. And those strawberry tarts are delicious. Did you try the pline cake?
一流美食。还有草莓馅饼。你有没有吃松饼？
Try it again.
再来一次
-Did you try the-- -Pickering!
-你有没有吃… -皮克林！
Again, Eliza.
再来，伊莱莎
Cuppatea.
Cuppatea.
Oh, no.
Oh, no.
Can't you hear the difference?
你听不出区别吗？
Look, put your tongue forward until it squeezes on the top of your lower teeth.
把你的舌头前伸压压在下齿上
And then say '"cup.'"
And then say '"cup.'"
Then say '"of.'"
Then say '"of.'"
Then say '"cup, cup, cup, cup, of, of, of, of.'"
Then say '"cup, cup, cup, cup,
By Jove, Higgins, that was a glorious tea.
老天，希金斯，这茶真好喝
You finish the last strawberry tart. I couldn't eat another thing.
你把最后一块草莓饼吃了吧，我吃不下了
-I couldn't touch it. -Shame to waste it.
-我不想吃。 -浪费太可异了
Oh, it won't be wasted. I know somebody who's immensely fond of strawberry tarts.
不会浪费的。我知道有人最爱吃草莓饼
''Poor Professor Higgins
“可怜的希金斯教授
'"On he plods against all odds
“拼命工作不肯服输
'"Nine p.m., ten p.m.
“九点钟，十点钟
'"On through midnight every night
“每晚一直到午夜
'"One a.m., two a.m., three....'"
“一点钟，两点钟，三…”
Four.
四
Five.
五
Six marbles.
六个弹珠
I want you to read this and I want you to enunciate...
我要你清楚出念出来…
...every word just as if the marbles were not in your mouth.
…一字一句，好象嘴里没弹珠
'"With blackest moss, the flower pots...
“花盆里长青苔…
'"...were thickly crusted, one and all.'"
“一片片硬又厚”
Each word, clear as a bell.
每个词要象钟声一样清楚
'"With blackest moss the flower...
“花盆里长青苔…
'"...pots.'"
'"...pots.'"
I can't!
不行！
I say, Higgins, are those pebbles really necessary?
我说，希金斯，有必要放这些石子吗？
If they were necessary for Demosthenes they are necessary for Eliza Doolittle.
古希腊演说家都是这么训练的
Go on, Eliza.
继续，伊莱莎
'"With the blackest moss the flower pots...
“花盆里长青苔…
'"...were thickly crusted one and--'"
“一片片硬又厚”
I can't understand a word, not a word.
我一个字都听不清
'"With blackest moss, the flower pots...
“花盆里长青苔…
'"...were thickly crusted, one and all.'"
“一片片硬又厚”
Perhaps the poem is a little too difficult for the girl.
也许念诗对这姑娘来说太难了
Why don't you try something simpler, like The Owl and the Pussycat?
你试试简单点的儿歌，比如“猫头鹰和猫咪”？
Yes, that's a charming one.
那首儿歌很棒的
Pickering, I can't hear a word the girl is saying!
皮克林，这姑娘说的我一个字都听不清！
What's the matter?
怎么了？
I swallowed one.
我吞掉了一个
It doesn't matter. I've got plenty more. Open your mouth. One, two....
没关系，我还有很多。张开嘴，一，二…
''Quit, Professor Higgins
“放弃吧，希金斯教授
'"Hear our plea, or payday we will quit
“再不听我们的请求，到发薪日我们就辞职
'"Professor Higgins!
“希金斯教授！
'"'Ay' not 'l', 'O' not 'ow'
“Ay不是I，O不是Ow
'"Pounding, pounding in our brain
“脑子里老是在重复
'"Don't say 'rine' say 'rain''"
“别说rine要就rain”
'"The rain in Spain...
“西班牙的雨…
'"...stays mainly in the plain.'"
“都下在平原上”
I can't!
我不行！
I'm so tired!
我太累了！
I'm so tired.
我真的太累了
For God's sake, Higgins, it must be 3:00 in the morning.
老天，希金斯，已经凌晨3点了
Do be reasonable.
理智一点
I am always reasonable.
我一向很理知
Eliza, if I can go on with a blistering headache, you can.
伊莱莎，我头这么痛都能坚持，你也行
I got a 'eadache, too.
我也头痛
I know your head aches. I know you're tired.
我知道你头痛。我知道你很累
I know your nerves are as raw as meat in a butcher's window.
我知道你神经感到麻木
But think what you're trying to accomplish.
但想象一下你就要成功了
Just think what you're dealing with.
想想看你该怎么做
The majesty and grandeur of the English language....
英国语言的神奇美妙…
It's the greatest possession we have.
是我们最宝贵的财富
The noblest thoughts that ever flowed through the hearts of men...
最高贵的思想从人心中流出…
...are contained in its extraordinary, imaginative...
…承载在这充满非凡想象力的…
...and musical mixtures of sounds.
…音乐般悦耳的声音之中
And that's what you've set yourself out to conquer, Eliza.
这就是你要所要征服的，伊莱莎
And conquer it you will.
你一定能够征服它
Now try it again.
现在再试一遍
'"The rain in Spain...
“西班牙的雨…
'"...stays mainly in the plain.'"
“…都下在平原上”
What was that?
什么？
'"The rain in Spain...
“西班牙的雨…
'"...stays mainly in the plain.'"
“…都下在平原上”
Again.
再来
'"The rain in Spain stays mainly in the plain.'"
“西班牙的雨都下在平原上”
I think she's got it.
我想她做到了
'"The rain in Spain Stays mainly in the plain
“西班牙的雨都下在平原上
'"By George, she's got it By George, she's got it
“老天，她做到了，老天，她做到了
'"Now once again Where does it rain?
“现在再来一次，雨下在哪里？
'"On the plain, on the plain
“在平原上，在平原上
'"And where's that soggy plain?
“那平原在哪里
'"ln Spain, in Spain
“在西班牙，在西班牙
'"The rain in Spain Stays mainly in the plain
“西班牙的雨都下在平原上
'"ln Hartford, Hereford and Hampshire
“在哈特福德、赫福德和汉普郡
'"Hurricanes hardly happen
“从不刮飓风”
'"How kind of you to let me come
“你让我来真是太好了
'"Now once again Where does it rain?
“现在再来一次，雨下在哪里？
'"On the plain, on the plain
“在平原上，在平原上
'"And where's that blasted plain?
“那平原在哪里
'"ln Spain, in Spain
“在西班牙，在西班牙
'"The rain in Spain Stays mainly in the plain'"
“西班牙的雨都下在平原上
We're making fine progress, Pickering. I think the time has come to try her out.
我们大有进展，皮克林。我们该让她出去试试
Are you feeling all right, Mr. Higgins?
你还好吗，希金斯？
Yes, I'm feeling fine. How are you?
我很好，你呢？
-Very well, thank you. -Good.
-很好，谢谢。 -好
Let's test her in public and see how she fares.
我们到公共场合去看她表现如何
Mr. Higgins, I was awakened by a dreadful pounding.
希金斯先生，我被很大的声响吵醒
Do you know what it might have been?
你知道发生什么事了？
I didn't hear any pounding. Did you, Pickering?
我没听到什么声响，你呢，皮克林？
If this goes on, you'd better see a doctor.
如果是这样，你最好去看看医生
-I know. We'll take her to the races. -The races?
-我知道，我们带她去赛马场。 -赛马场？
My mother's box at Ascot.
我母亲在爱斯科赛马场有的包厢
-You'll consult your mother first, of course. -Yes, of course.
-你当然应该先和你母亲商量。 -对，当然
No, I think we'd better surprise her. Now let's go to bed.
不，我想最好还是给她个惊喜。快去睡吧
First thing in the morning, we'll go and buy her a dress.
明早第一件事，我们要去给她买衣服
Now get on with your work, Eliza.
现在你继续练习，伊莱莎
But, Mr. Higgins, it's early in the morning.
可是，希金斯教授，已经是清早了
What better time to work than early in the morning?
还有比清早更好的练习时间吗？
Where does one buy a lady's gown?
去什么地方买女士的衣服？
Whitely's, of course.
当然是怀特利
How do you know that?
你怎么知道？
Common knowledge.
人人都知道
Let's not buy her anything too flowery.
我们别给她买太华丽的
I despise those gowns with weeds here and weeds there.
我讨厌那种太花哨的衣服
We'll buy something simple and modest...
我们要买简单得体…
...and elegant. That's what's called for.
…又高雅的。应该是这样
Perhaps with a bow.
比如带蝴蝶结的
Yes. That's just right.
对，那样很好
You've all been working too hard. I think the strain is beginning to show.
你们工作太久了，明显劳累过度
Eliza, I don't care what Mr. Higgins says.
伊莱莎，我不管希金斯先生怎么说
You must put down your books and go to bed.
你一定要放下书上床去
'"Bed! Bed! I couldn't go to bed
“床！床！我不能上床睡觉
'"My head's too light to try to set it down
“我的头脑轻飘飘的躺不牢
'"Sleep! Sleep! I couldn't sleep tonight
“睡！睡！我今晚无法入睡
'"Not for all the jewels in the crown!
“就算给我王冠上所有珠宝
'"l could have danced all night
“我可以整晚跳舞
'"And still have begged for more
“跳过了还要再跳
'"l could have spread my wings
“我可以展翅高飞
'"And done a thousand things
“再去做各种各样
'"l've never done before
“我从未做过的事
'"l'll never know what made it so exciting
“我不知道为何兴奋
'"Why all at once my heart took flight
“为何我的心会飞翔
'"l only know when he
“我只知道当他
'"Began to dance with me
“开始与我共舞
'"l could have danced, danced, danced...
“我可以一直跳舞，跳舞，跳舞…
'"...all night! '"
“整晚不停！”
It's after three now.
现在都三点多了
Don't you agree now?
应该可以了吧？
She ought to be in bed!
她应该上床睡觉！
'"l could have danced all night
“我可以整晚跳舞
'"And still have begged for more
“跳过了还要再跳
'"l could have spread my wings
“我可以展翅高飞
'"And done a thousand things
“再去做各种各样
'"l've never done before
“我从未做过的事
'"l'll never know what made it so exciting
“我不知道为何兴奋
'"Why all at once my heart took flight
“为何我的心会飞翔
'"l only know when he
“我只知道当他
'"Began to dance with me
“开始与我共舞
'"l could have danced, danced, danced...
“我可以一直跳舞，跳舞，跳舞…
'"...all night! '"
“整晚不停！”
It's all been grand, dear.
太好了，亲爱的
But now it's time to sleep!
但现在该去睡了！
'"l could have danced all night
“我可以整晚跳舞
'"And still have begged for more
“跳过了还要再跳
'"l could have spread my wings
“我可以展翅高飞
'"And done a thousand things
“再去做各种各样
'"l've never done before
“我从未做过的事
'"l'll never know what made it so exciting
“我不知道为何兴奋
'"Why all at once my heart took flight
“为何我的心会飞翔
'"l only know when he
“我只知道当他
'"Began to dance with me
“开始与我共舞
'"l could have danced, danced, danced...
“我可以一直跳舞，跳舞，跳舞…
'"...all night! '"
“整晚不停！”
'"Every duke and earl and peer is here
“每位王公贵族都来了
'"Everyone who should be here is here
“所有该来的都在这儿
'"What a smashing, positively dashing
“多么繁花似锦的场面
'"Spectacle, the Ascot opening day
“爱斯科盛大的开赛日
'"At the gate are all the horses
“所有赛马聚在大门前
'"Waiting for the cue to fly away
“只等一声令下就起跑
'"What a gripping, absolutely ripping
“多么引人注目的时刻
'"Moment at the Ascot opening day
“爱斯科盛大的开赛日
'"Pulses rushing
“脉搏在加速
'"Faces flushing
“面色全涨红
'"Heartbeats speed up
“心脏在狂跳
'"l have never been so keyed up!
“我从未如此紧张！
'"Any second now
“时间就要到来
'"They'll begin to run
“他们就要开始
'"Hark! A bell is ringing
“听！钟声响了
'"They are springing forward. Look!
“他们冲出去了！
'"lt has begun
“比赛已开始了
'"What a frenzied moment that was
“多么疯狂的时刻
'"Didn't they maintain an exhausting pace?
“他们好象不知疲倦？
'"lt was a thrilling, absolutely chilling
“这是多么紧张刺激
'"Running of the Ascot opening race! '"
“爱斯科公开赛马会！”
Mother!
母亲！
Henry! What a disagreeable surprise.
亨利！你吓我一跳
Hello, Mother.
嗨，母亲
How nice you look.
你气色真好
What are you doing here? You promised never to come to Ascot. Go home.
你在这儿干什么？你说不来爱斯科的，回去
I can't. I'm here on business.
不行，我有正经事要办
You must. I'm quite serious. You'll offend all my friends.
我是认真的，你这会得罪我的朋友
The moment they meet you I never see them again.
他们见了你以后就没来看我
Besides, you aren't dressed for Ascot.
再说你的穿着不适合看赛马
I changed my shirt. Mother, I've got a job for you.
我换了衬衣。妈妈，我要你帮个忙
A phonetics job. I've picked up a girl.
有关语音学的。我找了个姑娘
Not a love affair. She's a flower girl.
不是在恋爱。她是个卖花女
I'm taking her to the annual Embassy Ball but I wanted to try her out first.
我带她来参加年度使馆舞会，需要先测试一下
-I beg your pardon? -Well, you know the Embassy Ball.
-你什么意思？ -你知道使馆舞会
So I invited her to your box today, do you understand?
我带她来你的包厢，你明白了？
Common flower girl?
普通卖花女？
I taught her how to speak properly.
我已经教会她正确的谈吐
She has strict instructions as to her behavior.
她的举止也得到严格指导
She's to keep to two subjects: the weather and everybody's health.
她准备了两个话题：天气和健康
'"Fine day! '" and '"How do you do?'" Not let herself go on.
“好天气！”“你好吗？”。得有人陪她
Help her along. You'll be quite safe.
帮她的忙。你没问题的
Safe? To talk about one's health in the middle of a race?
没问题？赛马的时候谈健康话题？
She's got to talk about something.
她总得谈点什么
Where is the girl now?
那姑娘在哪儿？
She's being pinned. Some of the clothes we bought her didn't fit.
她被钩住了，她的衣服不合身
I told Pickering we should have taken her with us.
我告诉皮克林我们得带她来
-Mrs. Eynsford-Hill. -Good afternoon, Mrs. Higgins.
-恩福希尔太太。 -下午好，希金斯太太
You know my son, Henry.
你认得我儿子吧，亨利
How do you do?
你好吗？
-I've seen you somewhere before. -I don't know.
-我以前见过你。 -我不记得了
It doesn't matter. You better sit down.
没关系。请坐
Where the devil can they be?
他们到底去那儿了？
Colonel Pickering, you're just in time for tea.
皮克林上校，你正赶上喝茶
Thank you, Mrs. Higgins. May I introduce Miss Eliza Doolittle?
谢谢。我给你介绍伊莱莎杜利特小姐
My dear Miss Doolittle.
亲爱的杜利特小姐
How kind of you to let me come.
你让我来真是太好了
Delighted, my dear.
我很高兴，亲爱的
-Lady Boxington. -How do you do?
-伯克星顿夫人。 -你好吗？
-Lord Boxington.
-伯克星顿勋爵。 -你好吗？
How do you do?
你好吗？
-Mrs. Eynsford-Hill, Miss Doolittle. -How do you do?
-恩福希尔太太，杜利特小姐
And Freddy Eynsford-Hill.
福雷迪恩福希尔
Miss Doolittle.
杜利特小姐
Good afternoon, Professor Higgins.
下午好，希金斯教授
The first race was very exciting, Miss Doolittle.
第一场比赛很精采的，杜利特小姐
I'm so sorry that you missed it.
你错过了真可惜
Will it rain, do you think?
你觉得会下雨吗？
'"The rain in Spain stays mainly in the plain.'"
“西班牙的雨都下在平原上”
'"But in Hartford, Hereford and Hampshire, hurricanes hardly ever happen.'"
“但在哈特福德、赫福德和汉普郡从不刮飓风”
How awfully funny.
真有意思
What is wrong with that, young man? I bet I got it right.
怎么了，小伙子？我想我没说错吧
Smashing.
真了不起
Has it suddenly turned chilly?
天气会不会突然转冷？
I do hope we won't have any unseasonable cold spells.
我希望冷空气不会意外降临
They bring on so much influenza.
它会带来流行感冒
And the whole of our family is susceptible to it.
我们一家人都很容易传染
My aunt died of influenza, so they said.
他们说我姑妈就死于流行感冒
But it's my belief they done the old woman in.
但我觉得是他们把老太太做掉的
Done her in?
把她做掉？
Yes, Lord love you.
对，上帝保佑你
Why should she die of influenza...
她怎么可能死于流行感冒…
...when she'd come through diphtheria right enough the year before.
…前年她得白喉都没死
Fairly blue with it she was.
当时她气色差极了
They all thought she was dead.
他们都以为她已经死了
But my father, he kept ladling gin down her throat.
可我父亲不停地给她喂杜松子酒
Then she come to so sudden she bit the bowl off the spoon.
然后她突然缓过来了，还咬断了勺子
Dear me!
我的天！
Now what call would a woman with that strength in her...
所以说她的力气大得很…
...have to die of influenza?
…怎么会死于流行感冒？
And what become of her new straw hat that should have come to me?
还有她本来要给我的那顶新草帽哪去了？
Somebody pinched it.
给人偷走了
And what I say is:
所以我说：
Them 'as pinched it, done her in.
他们将草帽偷走，又把她做掉
Done her in? '"Done her in,'" did you say?
把她做掉？“把她做掉”，这样说对吗？
Whatever does it mean?
这句话是什么意思？
That's the new small talk. '"To do somebody in'" means to kill them.
这是个新短语，“做掉某人”意谓杀了他
But you surely don't believe your aunt was killed?
可你不会真以为你姑妈是被谋杀的吧？
Do I not?
怎么不会？
Them she lived with would have killed her for a hatpin, let alone a hat.
他们为了一根帽针也会杀了她，更别说是帽子
But it can't have been right for your father...
但你父亲的治病方法不太对…
...to pour spirits down her throat like that.
…给她灌烈性酒
It might have killed her.
可能是酒精杀死她的
Not her. Gin was mother's milk to her.
不可能。她喝杜松子酒就跟婴儿吃奶一样
Besides, he poured so much down his own throat he knew the good of it.
而且他自己也喝了不少，知道这有用
Do you mean that he drank?
你是说他喝醉了？
Drank? My word. Something chronic.
喝醉？要我说还差得远
Here, what are you sniggering at?
喂，你干嘛冲我笑？
The new small talk. You do it so awfully well.
那句新短语，你说得太好了
Well, if I was doing it proper, what was you sniggering at?
既然我没说错，那你干嘛冲我笑？
Have I said anything I oughtn't?
我说了不该说的话吗？
Not at all, my dear.
没有，亲爱的
Well, that's a mercy anyhow.
嗯，你真好
I don't know if there's time before the next race to place a bet...
我不知道是否来得及为这一场下注
...but come, my dear.
…来看看，亲爱的
I have a bet on number seven. I should be so happy if you would take it.
我下注给了7号，真希望你也选它
You'll enjoy the race ever so much more.
这样你更能体会赛马的乐趣
That's very kind of you.
你真是太好了
His name is Dover.
他名字叫多佛
Come along.
来吧
'"There they are again
“他们将要再出发
'"Lining up to run
“起跑线上排好队
'"Now they're holding steady
“人人把稳马缰绳
'"They are ready for it. Look!
“他们都已准备好。看！
'"lt has begun'"
“开始了”
Come on. Come on, Dover.
加油，加油，多佛
Come on.
加油
Come on, Dover!
加油，多佛！
Come on!
加油！
Move your bloomin' arse!
加油，多佛！摆起你的大屁股！
Oh, my dear.
哦，我的天
You're not serious, Henry. You don't expect to take her to the Embassy Ball.
你不当真吧，亨利。不要带她去使馆舞会
Don't you think she's ready for it?
你不认为她准备好了吧？
Dear Henry, she's ready for a canal barge.
亲爱的亨利，她只配上货船
Her language may need a little refining, but--
她的语言运用还不太得当，但…
Really, Henry, if you cannot see how impossible this whole project is...
真的，亨利。就算你不认为这计划不可能实现…
...then you must be potty about her.
…你也该为她着想
I advise you to give up and not put yourself...
我建议你放弃，不要将你自己…
...or this poor girl through any more.
还有这位可怜的姑娘置于更加难堪的境地
It's the most fascinating venture I've ever undertaken.
这是我经历过的最刺激的冒险
Pickering and I are at it from morning till night. It fills our whole lives.
皮克林和我一天到晚工作，别的事都不管
Teaching Eliza, talking to Eliza, listening to Eliza, dressing Eliza.
教育伊莱莎，跟她说，听她讲，为她打扮
You're a pretty pair of babies playing with your live doll.
你们就像是一对玩布娃娃的婴儿
Here's the car.
车来了
Good evening, sir.
晚上好，先生
-Is dinner ready? I'm famished. -Immediately, sir.
-晚饭好了吗？我饿极了。 -马上好，先生
Good evening, Professor Higgins.
晚上好，希金斯教授
'"When she mentioned how her aunt bit off the spoon
“当她说起她姑妈怎么咬断勺子
'"She completely done me in
“她已彻底把我做掉
'"And my heart went on a journey to the moon
“我的心已飞往月球
'"When she told about her father and the gin
“当她讲到她父亲和杜松子酒
'"And I never saw a more enchanting farce
“我从未见过比这更迷人的场面
'"Than the moment when she shouted 'Move your bloomin'--''"
“当她喊起那声‘摆起你的大――’”
-Yes, sir? -Is Miss Doolittle in?
-有事吗，先生？ -杜利特小姐在吗？
Whom shall I say is calling?
请问你是哪位？
Freddy Eynsford-Hill. If she doesn't remember who I am...
弗雷迪恩福希尔。要是她记不起我是谁…
...tell her I'm the chap who was '"sniggering'" at her.
…告诉她我是那个“冲她笑”的家伙
Yes, sir.
好吧，先生
And will you give her these?
你能带给她这个吗？
Wouldn't you like to come in?
你愿意进来吗？
They're having dinner, but you may wait in the hall.
他们在用餐，你可以先在门厅等
No, thank you. I want to drink in the street where she lives.
不，谢谢。我想在她住的街上喝一杯
'"l have often walked down this street before
“以前我经常走过这条街
'"But the pavement always stayed beneath my feet before
“以前人行道总是很坚固
'"All at once am I several stories high
“突然间我飞起几层楼高
'"Knowing I'm on the street where you live
“因为知道你住在这条街
'"Are there lilac trees in the heart of town?
“市中心会不会有丁香树？
'"Can you hear a lark in any other part of town?
“其他街区有没有云雀鸣？
'"Does enchantment pour out of every door?
“魔力能从所有门里涌出？
'"No, it's just on the street where you live
“不，只有你住的这条街
'"And, oh, the towering feeling
“哦，这飘飘欲仙的感觉
'"Just to know somehow you are near
“是因为知道你所在不远
'"The overpowering feeling
“这是种无法抗拒的感觉
'"That any second you may suddenly appear
“想到你也许会忽然出现
'"People stop and stare, they don't bother me
“人们停下看我，没关系
'"For there's nowhere else on earth that I would rather be
“因为别处我都不愿停留
'"Let the time go by
“让时间流逝
'"l won't care if I
“我不会在乎
'"Can be here on the street where you live'"
“只要我能留在你住的这条街”
I'm terribly sorry, sir.
很抱歉，先生
Miss Doolittle says she doesn't want to see anyone ever again.
杜利特小姐说不想再见任何人
But why? She was unbelievable.
为什么？真是难以理解
So I've been told, sir. Is there any further message?
她就是这么说的，先生。还要我带口信吗？
Tell her that I'll wait.
告诉她我在外面等
But it might be days, sir, even weeks.
可是也许要等几天，先生，甚至几个星期
But don't you see? I'll be happier here.
你看不出来吗？我很乐意等
'"People stop and stare, they don't bother me
“人们停下看我，没关系
'"For there's nowhere else on earth that I would rather be
因为别处我都不愿停留
'"Let the time go by
“让时间流逝
'"l won't care if I
“我不会在乎
'"Can be here on the street where you live'"
“只要我能留在你住的这条街”
It really is, Higgins. It's inhuman to continue.
真的，希金斯。继续下去是不人道的
Do you realize what you've got to teach this girl in six weeks?
你明白在六星期内你要教多少东西给这姑娘吗？
You've got to teach her to walk, talk, address a duke, a lord...
你得教她走路、说话；如何称呼公爵、勋爵
...a bishop, an ambassador. It's absolutely impossible.
…主教、大使。这是完全不可能的
Higgins, I'm trying to tell you that I want to call off the bet.
希金斯，我真心真意劝你，取消打赌
I know you're a stubborn man, but so am l.
我知道你是个固执的人，但我也是
This experiment is over.
这个试验结束了
And nothing short of an order from the king could force me to recant.
除非国王亲自命令，我才会放弃
You understand, Higgins? It's over.
你明白吗，希金斯？结束了
Higgins, if there's any mishap at the Embassy tonight...
希金斯，如果今晚使馆发生任何意外…
...if Miss Doolittle suffers any embarrassment...
…如果杜利特小姐陷入窘境
...it'll be on your head alone.
…责任都要算到你一个人头上
Eliza can do anything.
伊莱莎能做到任何事
Suppose she's discovered? Remember Ascot.
万一她被揭穿呢？想想埃斯科
Suppose she makes another ghastly mistake?
万一她再犯一次可怕的错误？
There'll be no horses at the ball, Pickering.
舞会上不会有马，皮克林
Think of how agonizing it would be.
想想出事后怎么办
If anything happened tonight, I don't know what I'd do.
如果今晚出了事，我不知该怎么办
You could always rejoin your regiment.
你还可以回你的军队去
This is no time for flippancy, Higgins.
草率行事是不行的，希金斯
The way you've driven her the last six weeks...
六星期来你训练她的方式…
...has exceeded all bounds of common decency.
…从任何方面说都违反常规
For God's sake, stop pacing. Can't you settle somewhere?
天哪，别踱来踱去了，你坐一会好吗？
Have some port. It'll quieten your nerves.
喝点葡萄酒。能缓解你的紧张
I'm not nervous.
我不紧张
-Where is it? -On the piano.
-在哪儿？ -钢琴上面
The car's here, sir.
车来了，先生
Good. Tell Miss Doolittle.
好，通知杜利特小姐
Tell Miss Doolittle indeed. I'll bet you that damned gown doesn't fit.
得通知杜利特小姐，我认为那件衣服不好
I warned you about these French designers.
我说过不要找法国设计师
We should've gone to an English shop. They would've been on our side.
应该去我们英国人开的店比较适合
-Have a glass of port? -No, thank you.
-来杯葡萄酒吗？ -不用，谢谢你
Are you so sure this girl will retain everything you've hammered into her?
你确信这姑娘能记住你教她的一切礼节？
Well, we shall see.
嗯，走着瞧吧
Suppose she doesn't?
万一她不能呢？
I lose my bet.
算我赌输了
There's one thing I can't stand about you, your confounded complacency.
我最受不了你这一点，太自以为是
At a moment like this, with so much at stake...
在这种时候，情形如此紧张
...it's utterly indecent that you don't need a glass of port.
…我认为你需要喝一杯葡萄酒
And what about the girl? You act as though she doesn't matter at all.
那姑娘怎么样了？你看起来当她一点不重要
Rubbish, Pickering. Of course she matters.
胡说，皮克林。她当然很重要
What do you think I've been doing all these months?
你以为这几个月我在忙什么？
What could possibly matter more than to take a human being...
还有什么事情比得上将一个人…
...and change her into a different human being by creating a new speech for her?
…通过改变她的语音而变成另一个人更重要？
It's filling up the deepest gap that separates class from class...
它填补了世上最深的鸿沟，阶级之间的…
...and soul from soul.
…和灵魂之间的
Oh, she matters immensely.
哦，她无比重要
Miss Doolittle, you look beautiful.
杜利特小姐，你看起来很美
Thank you, Colonel Pickering.
谢谢你，皮克林上校
Don't you think so, Higgins?
你觉得呢，希金斯？
Not bad. Not bad at all.
不错，确实不错
Maestro! Maestro!
大师！大师！
Don't you remember me?
你不记得我？
No. Who the devil are you?
不。你究竟是哪位？
I'm your pupil. Your first, your greatest, your best pupil.
我是你的学生。你最早最好最出色的学生
I'm Zoltan Karpathy, that marvelous boy.
我是佐坦卡帕西，当年那个好孩子
I made your name famous throughout Europe.
我使你在全欧洲扬名
You teach me phonetics. You can't forget me.
你教过我语音学，你一定没忘记我
Why don't you have your hair cut?
你怎么不把头发理整齐点？
I don't have your imposing appearance, your figure, your brow.
我可没有你这么气宇轩昂的形象
If I had my hair cut, nobody would notice me.
如果我头发再不特别一点，谁都不会注意我
Where did you get these old coins?
你这些旧硬币是哪弄来的
These are decorations for languages.
这些是代表各种语言的胸章
The Queen of Transylvania is here.
特兰西瓦尼亚的女王到了这里
I'm indispensable to her at these official international parties.
这种国际性的正式聚会她必定要带上我
I speak 32 languages. I know everyone in Europe.
我会讲32种语言，我在欧洲交游很广
No imposter can escape my detection.
没有哪个骗子能逃过我的法眼
Professor Karpathy.
卡帕西教授
The Greek ambassador.
那是希腊大使
Greek, my foot!
希腊是我的故乡！
He pretends not to know English, but he can't deceive me.
他假装不会英语，但他骗不了我
He's the son of a Yorkshire watchmaker.
他是约克郡一个钟表匠的儿子
He speaks English so villainously that he cannot utter a word...
他口音重极了，只要说一个词…
...without betraying his origin.
…就会被我揭穿底细
I help him pretend, but make him pay through the nose. I make them all pay.
我会让他装下去，但总得让他们付出代价
Excuse me, sir, you are wanted upstairs. Her Excellency asked for you.
对不起，先生，请到楼上来。女王要见你
Viscount and Viscountess Saxon.
萨克森子爵和子爵夫人
Baron and Baroness of Yorkshire.
约克郡男爵和男爵夫人
Sir Guy and Lady Scot-Auckland.
盖伊爵士和斯科特奥克兰夫人
The Count and Countess Demereau.
迪梅鲁伯爵和伯爵夫人
The Viscount and Viscountess Hillyard.
希尔雅德子爵和子爵夫人
Mr. and Mrs. Richard Lanser.
理查兰舍先生和夫人
Lord and Lady Clanders.
克兰德斯勋爵和夫人
Miss Eliza Doolittle, Colonel Pickering.
伊莱莎杜利特小姐，皮克林上校
Professor Higgins.
希金斯教授
-Your Excellency. -Miss Doolittle.
-阁下。 -杜利特小姐
How do you do?
你好吗？
-Good evening, Colonel. -Good evening.
-晚上好，上校。 -晚上好
What an enchanting young lady you have with you this evening.
你身边的这位年轻女士真迷人
Well, who is she?
嗯，她是哪一位？
Oh, a cousin of mine. And Higgins. Excuse me.
哦，是我，还有希金斯的表亲。对不起
Professor Higgins.
希金斯教授
Such a faraway look, as if she's always lived in a garden.
她的眼神好特别，看起来象长期住在花园里
So she has. A sort of garden.
正是。差不多是花园
Henry must take Eliza home at once. There's a language expert here.
亨利得立即带伊莱莎回去，这里有位语言专家
-Sort of, you know, '"imposterologist.'" -I beg you pardon?
-所谓的“抓骗子专家”。 -你说什么？
The young lady with Colonel Pickering....
和皮克林上校一起的那位年轻女士…
Find out who she is.
查清她是谁
With pleasure.
遵命
The whole situation is highly explosive.
情况非常危险
Tell me, Zoltan, some more about the Greek ambassador.
告诉我，佐坦，有关那希腊大使的详细情况
Gladly, but first I would love you to present me to this glorious creature.
很乐意，但首先我想要你把我介绍给这个人
Does he really come from Yorkshire?
他真是约克郡人吗？
Her Majesty, the Queen of Transylvania...
特兰西瓦尼亚女王陛下…
...and His Royal Highness Prince Gregor.
…和格雷戈亲王殿下
Charming. Quite charming.
迷人。很迷人
Miss Doolittle, Madam.
是杜利特小姐
Miss Doolittle, my son would like to dance with you.
杜利特小姐，我的儿子希望能与你共舞
Eliza.
伊莱莎
Absolutely fantastic.
太妙了
A lot of tomfoolery.
太愚蠢了
It was an immense achievement.
真是巨大的成功
Well, Mr. Higgins?
嗯，希金斯先生？
A triumph, Mrs. Pearce. A total triumph.
胜利，佩斯太太。彻底的胜利
Higgins, you were superb, absolutely superb.
希金斯，你是最棒的，绝对是最棒的
Tell us the truth now, weren't you a little bit nervous once or twice?
现在你说实话，你是否曾经感到过紧张？
Not during the whole evening?
整个晚上都没有过？
Not when I saw we were going to win.
我一直认为我们一定会赢
I felt like a bear in a cage hanging about.
我觉得就象有只出笼的熊在附近
It was an immense achievement.
真是巨大的成功
If I hadn't backed myself to do it, I'd have given up two months ago.
要是我决心不强，我两个月前就会放弃了
Absolutely fantastic.
真是太奇妙了
Yes, a lot of tomfoolery.
是的，很有想象力
Higgins, I salute you.
希金斯，我向你致敬
The silly people don't know their own silly business.
笨人们不知道自己多么愚笨
'"Tonight, old man, you did it You did it, you did it
“今晚，老伙计，你成功了，你成功了
'"You said that you would do it And indeed you did
“你说你能够做到，你说到做到
'"l thought that you would rue it I doubted you'd do it
“我以为你会懊悔，我不信你能做到
'"But now I must admit it That succeed you did
“现在我必须承认，你已获得成功
'"You should get a medal Or be even made a knight
“你应该得到奖章，甚至应该受封
'"Oh, it was nothing, really nothing
“哦，不算什么，真的不算什么
'"All alone you hurdled Every obstacle in sight
“你单枪匹马闯过艰难险阻
'"Now wait, now wait Give credit where it's due
“现在，现在，荣誉当之无愧
'"A lot of the glory goes to you
“光荣全都归于你
'"But you're the one who did it Who did it, who did it
“是你做到一切，你成功了，你成功了
'"As sturdy as Gibraltar Not a second did you falter
“象直布罗陀的岩壁一样坚定，从不动摇
'"There's no doubt about it
“对此再也没有疑问
'"You did it!
“你成功了！
'"l must have aged a year tonight At times I thought I'd die of fright
“今晚我老了整整一年，好几次吓得要死
'"Never was there a momentary lull
“虽然那儿一刻也不曾平静
'"Shortly after we came in I saw at once we'd easily win
“我到场不久就发现我们一定能赢
'"And after that I found it deadly dull
“缺乏挑战实在无趣
'"You should have heard The 'oohs' and 'aahs'
“你一定听到了惊叹的声音
'"Everyone wondering who she was
人人都想知道她是谁
'"You'd think they'd never seen a lady before
“他们仿佛从没见过真正的窈窕淑女
'"And when the Prince of Transylvania Asked to meet her
“当特兰西瓦尼亚王子邀请她
'"And gave his arm to lead her to the floor
“牵着她的手步入舞池
'"l said to him: 'You did it You did it, you did it'
“我对他讲：‘你成功了，你成功了’
'"They thought she was ecstatic And so damned aristocratic
“所有人都被她迷感，如此的高贵
'"And they never knew That you...
“他们永远也不会知道一切都是你…
'"...did it'"
“做到的”
Thank goodness for Zoltan Karpathy.
真要感谢佐坦卡帕西
If it hadn't been for him I would've died of boredom.
如果不是因为他，我会觉得更加无聊
Karpathy? That dreadful Hungarian? Was he there?
卡帕西？那个讨厌的匈牙利人？他也在？
Yes, he was there all right and up to his old tricks.
Yes, he was there all right
'"That blackguard Who uses the science of speech
“那个无赖研究语言学
'"More to blackmail and swindle than teach
“不为教书育人只为坑蒙拐谝
'"He made it the devilish business of his
“他费尽各种心机
'"To find out who this Miss Doolittle is
“只为查出杜利特小姐的底细
'"Every time we looked around There he was
“我们每次转头都能看见他
'"That hairy hound from Budapest
“这头布达佩斯来的长毛猎狗
'"Never leaving us alone Never have I ever known
“紧追着我的不放松
'"A ruder pest
“粗鲁的家伙
'"Finally I decided it was foolish Not to let him have his chance with her
“最后我决定不妨给他一个攀谈的机会
'"So I stepped aside And let him dance with her
“所以我退开好让他与她共舞
'"Oozing charm from every pore He oiled his way around the floor
“这使他志得意满晕头转向
'"Every trick that he could play He used to strip her mask away
“他使出浑身解数想摘下她的面具
'"And when at last the dance was done He glowed as if he knew he'd won
“当舞跳完他兴高采烈自以为成功
'"And with a voice too eager And a smile too broad
“激动万分乐不可支
'"He announced to the hostess That she was a fraud'"
“他向女主人宣称她是扮假者”
No!
不！
'"'Her English is too good,' he said 'That clearly indicates that she is foreign
“‘她的英语好得过分，’他讲‘一定是外国人
'"'Whereas others are instructed ln their native language
‘其他人是用其他语言来教英语
'"'English people aren't
‘英国人可不是
'"'Although she may have studied with an expert dialectician and grammarian
‘虽然她可能师从过一位语音语法专家
'"'l can tell that she was born
‘我还是能说出她的出生地
'"'Hungarian'
‘是匈牙利’
'"Not only Hungarian but of royal blood
‘而且是匈牙利王室成员
'"She is a princess
‘她是一位公主
'"'Her blood,' he said 'ls bluer than the Danube is or ever was
‘他的血统’他说‘就象蓝色多瑙河一样纯
'"'Royalty is absolutely written on her face
‘她的脸庞写明了王室的高贵
'"'She thought I was taken in But actually I never was
‘她以为能瞒过我其实我心知肚明
'"'How could she deceive Another member of her race?
‘她怎能骗过她自己的国民？
'"'l know each language on the map' Said he
‘我了解世界上所有的语言’他讲
'"'And she's Hungarian As the first Hungarian Rhapsody''"
‘她和匈牙利狂想曲一样都来自匈牙利’
'"Congratulations, Professor Higgins
“祝贺你，希金斯教授
'"For your glorious victory
“为了你光荣的胜利
'"You'll be mentioned in history'"
“你将会青史留名”
Well, thank God, that's over.
感谢上帝，都结束了
Now I can go to bed without dreading tomorrow.
现在我能安然入睡，不再为明天担心
-Good night, Mr. Higgins. -Good night, Mrs. Pearce.
再见，希金斯先生。再见，佩思太太
I think I'll turn in, too. Good night. It's been a great occasion.
我也要休息了。晚安。真是美好的经历
Good night, Pickering.
晚安，皮克林
Mrs. Pearce?
佩思太太？
Damn, I meant to ask her to give me coffee in the morning instead of tea.
见鬼，我本来让她早上别煮茶要煮咖啡
Leave a little note for her will you, Eliza. And put out the lights.
你给他留张条好吗，伊莱莎。再把灯灭掉
Must be downstairs. Oh, darn it.
应该丢在楼下，见鬼
I'll leave my head behind one of these days.
总有一天我会把我的脑袋也弄丢
What the devil have I done with my slippers?
我倒底把我的拖鞋放哪儿了？
Here are your slippers!
你的拖鞋在这里！
Take your slippers and may you never have a day's luck with them.
穿好你的拖鞋走你的霉运去
What on earth? What's the matter?
搞什么？出什么事啦？
Is anything wrong?
有什么问题？
No, nothing's wrong with you. I won your bet for you, haven't l?
没有，没你的事。我为你赢得赌赛，对吧？
That's enough for you! I don't matter, I suppose?
你认为这足够了！我无关紧要，是吗？
You won my bet? You presumptuous insect! I won it!
你为我赢得赌赛？你胡说！是我赢的！
Why did you throw the slippers at me?
你干嘛向我扔拖鞋？
Because I wanted to smash your face. I could kill you, you selfish brute!
因为我想打烂你的脸。打死你这自私鬼！
Why didn't you leave me where you picked me up?
你以为可以随便丢下我？
You thank God it's all over. Now you can throw me back again! Do you?
你感谢上帝一切结束了。我可以走了，是吗？
Oh, so the creature's nervous after all?
你这会儿发什么神经？
Claws in, you cat! How dare you show your temper to me?
别象只猫样张牙舞爪！你怎敢对我发火？
Sit down and be quiet!
老实坐好！
What's to become of me?
我将来怎么办？
How do I know what's to become of you?
我怎么知道你将来怎么办？
What does it matter?
跟我有什么关系？
You don't care. I know you don't care.
你漠不关心。我早知你不会关心
You wouldn't care if I was dead. I'm nothing to you.
我死了你也不会管，我什么都不是
Not as much as them slippers.
连那双拖鞋都比不上
Those slippers!
那双拖鞋！
Those slippers! I didn't think it meant any difference now.
那双拖鞋！和那双拖鞋没什么区别
Why have you suddenly begun going on like this?
你怎么忽然变得这个样子？
May I ask if you complain of your treatment here?
是不是你抱怨在这里受到虐待？
No.
不
Has anybody behaved badly? Colonel Pickering, Mrs. Pearce?
有谁待你不好？皮克林上校，佩斯太太？
Well you don't pretend that I have treated you badly?
那你意思就是说我待你不好？
No.
不
Well, I'm glad to hear that.
嗯，我很高兴
Perhaps you're tired after the strain of the day.
也许只是因为今天你太累了
Would you have a chocolate?
你想来块巧克力吗？
No, thank you.
不，谢谢你
Well, it's only natural that you should be anxious, but it's all over now.
嗯，以前感到担心并不奇怪，但现在都结束了
Nothing more to worry about.
没什么好担心的了
No, nothing more for you to worry about.
不，是你自己没什么好担心的了
Oh, God, I wish I was dead.
天哪，我还不如死了才好
Why? ln heaven's name, why?
为什么？到底是为什么？
Now listen to me, Eliza. All this irritation is purely subjective.
听我说，伊莱莎，你气生得毫无道理
I don't understand. I'm too ignorant.
我不明白，我一点都不理解
It's just imagination. Nothing's wrong. Nobody's hurting you.
是你胡思乱想，没有任何问题，没人要伤害你
Go to bed and sleep it off.
上床睡上一觉就好了
Have a little cry and say your prayers. You'll feel very much more comfortable.
哭一小会，念句祷词，你会平静下来的
I heard your prayers.
我听过你的褥词了
'"Thank God it's all over.'"
“感谢上帝一切都结束了”
Don't you thank God it's all over?
你不想感谢上帝一切都结束了？
Now you're free, and you can do what you like.
现在你自由了，你想做什么就可以做
Oh, what am I fit for? What have you left me fit for?
哦，我适合做什么？你说我适合做什么？
Where am I to go? What am I to do?
我能去哪里？我能做什么？
And what's to become of me?
我将来会怎样？
That's what's worrying you, is it?
你为这些事担心，是吗？
I wouldn't worry about that if I were you.
要我是你就不会为这些事担心
I'm sure you won't have any difficulty in settling yourself somewhere or other.
我确信你会毫不困难地找个地方安顿下来
I didn't quite realize you were going away.
我想你可以有很多选择
You might marry, you know.
比如说你可以结婚
You see, Eliza, all men are not confirmed old bachelors like me and the Colonel.
你知道不是所有男人都象我和上校宁愿做单身汉
Most men are the marrying sort, poor devils.
大多数男人都还是要结婚的
You're not bad-looking.
你长得不难看
You're really quite a pleasure to look at sometimes.
有时你看起来还是蛮不错的
Not now, when you've been crying.
当然不是现在，你哭相很难看
You look like the very devil, but...
现在你的样子象鬼，不过…
...when you're all right and quite yourself you're what I would call attractive.
你神智正常的时候得承认你可以说是很可爱
Go to bed, have a good rest, get up in the morning...
现在好好睡上一觉，早上起来时…
...and have a look at yourself in the glass. You won't feel so bad.
…再对着镜子瞧一瞧，你感觉会好起来
I daresay, my mother might find some fellow or other who would do very well.
我敢说，我母亲可以帮忙找到合你意的
We were above that at Covent Garden.
我们可不是在菜市场里
What do you mean?
你什么意思？
I sold flowers, I didn't sell myself.
我卖的是花，不是我自己
Now you've made a lady of me, I'm not fit to sell anything else.
你把我变成淑女，我什么事都做不了
Oh, tosh, Eliza. Don't insult human relations...
哦，伊莱莎。不要把人们之间的关系
...by dragging all that cant about buying and selling into it.
…总想成买卖东西
Don't marry the fellow if you don't want to.
你不想嫁人就不必勉强
What else am I to do?
那我还能做什么？
Oh, there are lots of things.
哦，事情多得是
What about the old idea of a florist shop?
比如你原来打算的去一家花店？
I'm sure Pickering'd set you up in one. He's got lots of money.
我确位皮克林会帮你找一家，他很有钱
He'll pay for all those togs you're wearing.
他会出钱给你买需要的好衣服
And that with the hire of the jewelry'll make a big hole in 200 pounds.
加上首饰的租金只怕要花上200镑
Come on now. You'll be all right.
好了，你会没事的
Well, I must be off to bed. I'm really devilish sleepy.
我可要马上睡觉，我困得要死
I was looking for something. What was it?
刚才我好象要找什么东西，是吗？
Your slippers.
你的拖鞋
Oh, yes, of course. You shied them at me.
对了，当然。你扔给我了
Before you go, sir.
还有一件事，先生
Do my clothes belong to me or to Colonel Pickering?
我这衣服属于我还是皮克林上校？
What the devil use would they be to Pickering?
皮克林拿去有什么用？
Why bother about that in the middle of the night?
深夜半夜的干嘛问这个？
What may I take away with me?
那我带走可以吗？
I don't want to be accused of stealing.
我不想被指控偷窃
Stealing?
偷窃？
You shouldn't have said that. That shows a want of feeling.
你不要这样讲，让人感觉很不好
I'm sorry. I'm a common, ignorant girl and in my station I have to be careful.
对不起。一个穷姑娘还是小心些比较好
There can't be any feelings between the likes of you and the likes of me.
你和我不是一类人，哪会有什么感觉
Please, will you tell me what belongs to me and what doesn't?
请告诉我哪些属于我那些不是？
Take the whole damned houseful if you want.
这屋里能带的都拿走好了
Except the jewelry. That's hired. Will that satisfy you?
除了珠宝首饰，那是租来的，你满意了吗？
Stop, please.
请先别走
Will you take these to your room and keep them safe?
请你把这些拿到你房间妥善保管
I don't want to run the risk of them being missed.
要是给弄丢了我可赔不起
Hand them over! lf these belonged to me and not the jeweler, I'd...
拿来！要是我自己而不是珠宝商的，我…
...l'd ram them down your ungrateful throat.
…我就用它扭断你的脖子
The ring isn't the jeweler's. It's the one you bought me in Brighton.
这戒指不是珠宝商的，是你在布雷顿买的
I don't want it now.
现在我也不想要了
Don't you hit me!
不要打我！
Hit you? You infamous creature! How dare you suggest such a thing!
打你？你这该死的！你怎敢这么说！
It's you who've hit me. You've wounded me to the heart.
是你在打我。是你使我痛心
I'm glad. I've got a little of my own back anyhow.
我高兴，我算是给自己报了一点仇
You've caused me to lose my temper. That's hardly happened to me before.
你让我发了脾气，我以前很少发火
I don't wish to discuss it further tonight. I'm going to bed.
我今晚不想再和你理论，我要去睡觉了
Leave your own note for Mrs. Pearce about the coffee...
你自己给佩思太太留条叫煮咖啡吧…
...for it won't be done by me!
…因为我没时间写！
Damn Mrs. Pearce, damn the coffee and damn you!
佩思太太、咖啡还有你都该死！
Damn my own folly for having lavished my hard-earned knowledge...
我也该死，无缘无故浪费自已积累的学识…
...and the treasure of my regard and intimacy on a heartless guttersnipe!
…和宝贵的耐心和信赖给一个无情的生物！
'"Just you wait, 'Enry 'lggins Just you wait!
“等着瞧，亨利希金斯，你等着瞧！
'"You'll be sorry But your tears will be too late
“你会伤心失望，流下悔恨的眼泪
'"You will be the one it's done to
“你到时会彻底完蛋
'"And you'll have no one to run to
“没人能再给你帮忙
'"Just you wait'"
“你等着瞧”
'"l have often walked down this street before
“以前我经常走过这条街
'"But the pavement always stayed beneath my feet before
“以前人行道总是很坚固
'"All at once am I several stories high
“突然间我飞起几层楼高
'"Knowing I'm on the street where you live
“因为知道你住在这条街
'"Are there lilac trees in the heart of town?
“市中心会不会有丁香树？
'"Can you hear a lark in any other part of town?
“其他街区有没有云雀鸣？
'"Does enchantment pour out of every door?
“魔力能从所有门里涌出？
'"No, it's just on the street where you live
“不，只有你住的这条街
'"And, oh, the towering feeling
“哦，这飘飘欲仙的感觉
'"Just to know somehow you are near
“是因为知道你所在不远
'"The overpowering feeling
“这是种无法抗拒的感觉
'"That any second you may suddenly appear
“想到你也许会忽然出现
'"People stop and stare, they don't....'"
“人们停下看我，没关系
Darling.
亲爱的
Freddy, whatever are you doing here?
弗雷迪，你在这儿干什么？
Nothing. I spend most of my nights here. It's the only place where I'm happy.
没什么。我已呆了大半夜，在这儿我最开心
Don't laugh at me, Miss Doolittle.
别笑我，杜利特小姐
Don't you call me '"Miss Doolittle,'" do you hear? Eliza's good enough for me.
不要叫我“杜利特小姐”，听到没有，我叫伊莱莎
Freddy, you don't think I'm a heartless guttersnipe, do you?
弗雷迪，你不认为我是个无情的生物，是吗？
Darling, how could you imagine such a thing? You know how I feel.
亲爱的，你怎么能这么想？你知道我的心情
I've written two and three times a day telling you. Sheets and sheets.
我每天都写好几封好几页纸的信给你
'"Speak, and the world is full of singing
“说一句话，世界象在歌唱
'"And I am winging higher than the birds
“我会象鸟儿一样飞翔
'"Touch, and my heart begins to crumble
“拉一下手，我的心会震颤
'"The heavens tumble Darling, and I'm--'"
“天空也会倾覆。亲爱的，我――
'"Words, words, words I'm so sick of words
“这些废话我都听厌了
'"l get words all day through First from him, now from you
“我每天都得听废话，以前是他，现在是你
'"ls that all you blighters can do?
“你们这帮讨厌鬼是不是只会这个？
'"Don't talk of stars burning above
“不要谈论天空的星星
'"lf you're in love, show me
“如果你爱我，让我看到
'"Tell me no dreams filled with desire
“不要告诉我希望的梦想
'"lf you're on fire, show me
“如果你有热情，让我看到
'"Here we are together ln the middle of the night
“既然夜半时分我们在一起
'"Don't talk of spring Just hold me tight
“不要谈论春天，只要将我抱紧
'"Anyone who's ever been in love'll Tell you that
“任何恋爱过的人都能告诉你该怎么做
'"This is no time for a chat
“没有时间去闲聊
'"Haven't your lips longed for my touch?
“难道你不希望现在吻我？
'"Don't say how much, show me
“不要说你多么希望，让我看到
'"Show me
“让我看到
'"Don't talk of love lasting through time
“不要谈论爱有多长久
'"Make me no undying vow
“不要海誓山盟
'"Show me now
“现在让让我看到
'"Sing me no song, read me no rhyme
“不要唱情歌，不要念情诗
'"Don't waste my time, show me
“不要浪费我的时间，让我看到
'"Don't talk of June, don't talk of fall
“不要谈论六月天，不要谈论金秋季
'"Don't talk at all, show me
“什么都不要谈论，让我看到
'"Never do I ever want to hear another word
“我不想再听一个字
'"There isn't one I haven't heard
“我已经全都听厌倦
'"Here we are together in what ought to be a dream
“我们在一起应该象是在梦境
'"Say one more word and I'll scream
“再多说一个字我就会生气
'"Haven't your arms hungered for mine?
“难道你不希望将我拥抱？
'"Please don't explain, show me
“不要多做解释，让我看到
'"Show me
“让我看到
'"Don't wait until wrinkles and lines
“别等到年华老去
'"Pop out all over my brow
“脸上布满皱纹
'"Show me now! '"
“现在就让我看到！”
-Where are you going? -To the river.
-你去哪里？ -去河边
-What for? -To make a hole in it.
-干什么？ -跳进去
Eliza, darling, what do you mean?
伊莱莎，亲爱的，你在说什么？
Taxi!
出租车！
-But I've no money. -I have.
-可我没钱。 -我有
-Where are we going? -Where I belong.
-我们去哪儿？ -去属于我的地方
Darling, shall I come with you?
亲爱的，我和你一起去好吗？
''With one enormous chair
“里面有把大躺椅
''Oh, wouldn't it be loverly?
“这难道不惬意？
''Lots of chocolate for me to eat
“许许多多的巧克力
''Lots of coal makin' lots of 'eat
“炭火烧得暖洋洋
''Warm face, warm 'ands, warm feet
“从头到脚都温暖
''Oh, wouldn't it be loverly?''
“这难道不惬意？
Buy a flower, miss?
买花吗？小姐？
Yes, please.
好的
Good morning, miss. Can I help you?
早上好，小姐。你有事吗？
Do you mind if I warm my hands?
我能烤一下火吗？
Go right ahead, miss.
行，小姐
Excuse me. For a second I thought you were somebody else.
对不起。我刚才把你错认成别人了
Who?
谁？
Forgive me, ma'am. Early morning light playing tricks with my eyes.
原谅我，女士。清早光线让我看花眼了
Can I get you a taxi? A lady shouldn't be walkin' alone...
我叫辆出租车来？一位女士不该单独走路…
...around London this hour of the morning.
…大清早的在伦敦城里
No, thank you.
不必，谢谢你
''Someone's head restin' on my knee
“和他偎依在一起
''Warm and tender as he can be
“温柔又甜蜜
''Who takes good care of me
“永远保护我
''Oh, wouldn't it...
“这难道…
''...be loverly?
“…不惬意？
''Loverly ''
“惬意”
Do come again, Mr. Doolittle. We value your patronage always.
“下回再来，杜利特先生。希望您经常光顾
Thank you, my good man. Thank you. Here. Come 'ere.
谢谢你，老兄，谢谢。喂，过来
Take the missus on a trip to Brighton with my compliments.
请代替我送这位女士去布雷顿吧
Thank you, Mr. Doolittle.
谢谢你，杜利特先生
Jolly spot this, Harry. We must visit it more often.
这里很不错，哈利。我一定常来
Father?
父亲？
Oh, no. You see, Harry, he has no mercy.
啊，不。你瞧，哈利，他真不讲情面
Sent her down to spy on me in me misery, he did. Me own flesh and blood.
是他又叫她来监视我，我自己的骨肉呀
Well, I'm miserable, all right. You can tell him that straight.
对，我混得很惨。你照直对他说就是了
What are you talking about? What are you dressed up for?
你说什么？穿这么整齐干嘛？
As if you didn't know.
你还装不知道
Go on back to that Wimpole Street devil. Tell him what he's done to me.
回去见那温坡街的魔鬼，都是他干的好事
What's he done to you?
他怎么着你了？
Ruined me, that's all.
毁了我，就是这样
Tied me up and delivered me into the hands of middle-class morality.
用什么混帐中产阶级道德捆牢了我
And don't you defend him.
你少为他辩护
Was it 'im or was it not 'im wrote to an old American blighter named Wallingford...
难道不是他写信给那个叫威林福的美国混蛋…
...who was giving $5,000,000 to found Moral Reform societies...
…那个出五百万创办道德重整协会家伙…
...to tell him the most original moralist in England was Mr. Alfred P. Doolittle...
…说全英国道德观最原始的人是我阿福雷杜利特…
...a common dustman?
…一个清洁工？
Sounds like one of his jokes.
他大概是开玩笑
You may call it a joke. It's put the lid on me. Proper.
你所谓的开玩笑可把我整惨了
The old bloke died and left me 4,000 pounds a year in his bloomin' will.
那老混蛋临死立遗嘱每年给我四千镑
Who asked him to make a gentleman outta me? I was 'appy. I was free.
谁要他把我变成绅士了？我本来快乐自由
I touched pretty nigh everyone for money when I wanted it, same as I touched him.
本来我可以随便找个人去要钱，象那次找他
Now I'm tied neck and 'eels and everybody touches me.
现在却给别人找上我
A year ago I 'adn't a relation in the world...
一年以前我无牵无挂…
...except one or two who wouldn't speak to me.
…仅有的几个亲戚话都不跟我讲
Now I've 50. Not a decent week's wages amongst the lot of them.
可现在我要养50个人，个个都来要钱
I have to live for others now, not for meself. Middle-class morality.
我在那别人而活而不是自己。中产阶级道德
Come on, Alfie, in a few hours we have to be at the church.
快，阿福雷，我们得尽快到教堂去
-Church? -Yeah, church.
-教堂？ -对，教堂
The deepest cut of all.
最狠的一招
Why do you think I'm dressed up like a ruddy pallbearer?
你以为我穿这这个整齐要去干什么？
Your stepmother wants to marry me.
你继母要和我结婚
Now I'm respectable, she wants to be respectable.
现在我有身份了，她也想有身份
If that's the way you feel, why don't you give the money back?
要是你这么想，干嘛不把钱还了？
That's the tragedy of it, Eliza.
最可悲就是这一点，伊莱莎
It's easy to say chuck it...
说起来容易…
...but I 'aven't the nerve.
…但我可没这种勇气
We're all intimidated. That's what we are, intimidated.
我们都是不得已，没错，不得已
Bought up. Yeah. That's what I am.
身不由已，是的，我就是这样
That's what your precious professor's brought me to.
这都是你那宝贝教授逼出来的
Not my precious professor.
什么我的宝贝教授
Oh, sent you back, 'as he?
噢，被赶出来了，是吗？
First he shoves me in the middle-class, then he chucks you out for me to support.
他先把我推进中产阶级，然后又把你推给我
That's all part of his plan...
这全都是他的诡计…
...but you double-cross him.
…但你又想出卖他
Don't you come back home to me. Don't you take tuppence from me.
你别来找我，你别想向我拿一个钱
You stand on your own two feet. You're a lady now, you can do it.
你得自立，你现在是位淑女，你能做到
Yeah, that's right, Eliza. You're a lady now.
就是这样，伊莱莎。你现在是位淑女了
It's getting awfully cold in that taxi.
出租车里真冷
Here, Eliza, would you like to come and see me turned off this morning?
喂，伊莱莎，你要去看我的婚礼吗？
St. George's, Hanover Square, 10:00.
十点整汉诺威广场圣乔治教堂
I wouldn't advise it, but you're welcome.
我不勉强你，但欢迎你来
No, thank you, Dad.
不了，谢谢，爸爸
Are you all finished here, Eliza?
这儿的事都办完了吗，伊莱莎？
Yes, Freddy, I'm all finished here.
是，弗雷迪，我的事都办完了
Good luck, Dad.
好运，爸爸
Thank you, Eliza.
谢谢，伊莱莎
Come along, Alfie.
快来，阿福雷
How much time have I got left?
我还剩多少时间？
'"There's just a few more hours
“还剩下几个小时
'"That's all the time you've got
“属于自己的时间
'"Before they tie the knot'"
“你就要系上锁链”
There's drinks and girls all over London.
伦敦城到处是美酒和女人
And I gotta track 'em down in just a few more hours.
剩下的几小时要尽情享乐
Set 'em up, me darlin'.
快准备好，亲爱的
'"l'm gettin' married in the mornin'
“我一早就要去结婚
'"Ding dong, the bells are gonna chime
“教堂钟声就要敲响
'"Pull out the stopper Let's have a whopper
“打开瓶塞痛饮一场
'"But get me to the church on time
“再准时送我到教堂
'"l got to be there in the mornin'
“我一早就要去教堂
'"Spruced up and looking in me prime
“打扮齐整象模象样
'"Girls, come and kiss me Show how you'll miss me
“姑娘们快将我亲吻
'"But get me to the church on time
“再准时送我到教堂
'"lf I am dancin' Roll up the floor
“尽情跳舞踏穿地板
'"lf I am whistlin' Me out the door
“口哨声响吵醒全城
'"For I'm getting married in the mornin'
“因为我一早就要去结婚
'"Ding dong, the bells are gonna chime
“教堂钟声就要敲响
'"Kick up a rumpus But don't lose the compass
“尽情狂欢但别晕头转向
'"And get me to the church
“再准时送我到教堂
'"For God's sake Get me to the church...
“请送我到教堂…
'"...on time
“…一定要准时
'"l'm gettin' married in the mornin'
“我一早就要去结婚
'"Ding dong, the bells are gonna chime
“教堂钟声就要敲响
'"Some bloke who's able Lift up the table
“有力气尽管掀翻桌子
'"But get me to the church on time
“但要准时送我到教堂
'"lf I am flyin' Then shoot me down
“我再乱飞就拿枪把我射下
'"lf I am wooin' Get her out of town
“我再沾花惹草就把她送走
'"For I'm getting married in the mornin'
“因为我一早就要去结婚
'"Ding dong, the bells are gonna chime
“教堂钟声就要敲响
'"Feather and tar me Call out the Army
“尽管来恶作剧动刀动枪
'"But get me to the church
“但送我到教堂
'"Get me to the church
“送我到教堂
'"For God's sake Get me to the church...
“劳驾送我到教堂…
'"...on time
“…一定要准时
'"He's gettin' married in the mornin'
“他一早就要去结婚
'"Ding dong, the bells are gonna chime
“教堂钟声就要敲响
'"Come on, pull out the stopper Let's have a whopper
“来打开瓶塞痛饮一场
'"But get me to the church on time
“但准时送我到教堂
'"He's got to be there in the mornin'
“他一早就要去教堂
'"Spruced up and lookin' in his prime
“打扮齐整象模象样
'"Girls, come and kiss me Show how you'll miss me
“姑娘们快将我亲吻
'"But get me to the church on time
“再准时送我到教堂
'"lf I am dancin' Roll up the floor
“尽情跳舞踏穿地板
'"lf I am whistlin' Me out the door
“口哨声响吵醒全城
'"Drug me or jail me Stamp me and mail me
“下药或送我进监牢，贴张邮票把我寄走
'"But get me to the church
“但送我到教堂
'"Get him to the church
“送他到教堂
'"For God's sake Get me to the church on time
“劳驾准时送我到教堂
'"Girls come and kiss him Show how they miss him
“姑娘们快将他亲吻
'"But get him to the church on time
但一定准时送他到教堂
'"Kick up a rumpus But don't lose the compass
“尽情狂欢但别晕头转向
'"And get him to the church on time
“再准时送他到教堂
'"lf I am flyin' Then shoot me down
“我再乱飞就拿枪把我射下
'"lf I am wooin' Get her out of town
“我再沾花惹草就把她送走
'"He's gettin' married in the mornin'
“他一早就要去结婚
'"Ding dong, the bells are gonna chime
“教堂钟声就要敲响
'"Some bloke who's able Lift up the table
“有力气尽管掀翻桌子
'"But get me to the church on time
“但要准时送我到教堂
'"Starlight is reelin' Home to bed now
“星星在渐渐隐去
'"Mornin' is smearin' up the sky
“清晨已经到来
'"London is wakin'
“伦敦正在苏醒
'"Daylight is breakin'
“开始新的一天
'"Good luck, old chum
“祝你好运，老伙计
'"Good health
“祝你健康
'"Goodbye
“走好
'"l'm gettin' married in the mornin'
“我一早就要去结婚
'"Ding dong, the bells are gonna chime
“教堂钟声就要敲响
'"Hail and salute me Then haul off and boot me
“为我欢呼，向我致敬，再送我一程
'"But get him to the church Get him to the church
“但送他到教堂，送他到教堂
'"For God's sake Get him to the church...
“劳驾送他到教堂…
'"...on time'"
“一定要准时”
Didn't she say where to send her clothes?
她没说把她的衣物送到哪里？
I told you, sir, she took them all with her.
我告诉你了，先生，她把衣物自己带走了
Here's a confounded thing. Eliza's bolted.
出麻烦了，伊莱莎跑了
Last night Mrs. Pearce let her go without telling me about it!
昨晚佩思太太自作主张让她走了！
What'll I do? I got tea this morning instead of coffee.
我怎么办？早上咖啡都没的喝
I don't know where anything is, what my appointments are.
我不知道东西放哪里，日程怎么安排的
-Eliza'd know. -Damn it, she's gone!
-伊莱莎知道。 -见鬼，她跑了！
Did either of you frighten her last night?
是不是你们昨晚说了她什么？
We hardly said a word to her. You were there.
我没对她说什么话，你也在场的
Did you bully her after I went to bed?
我去睡后你说她了？
She threw the slippers at me.
他把向我扔拖鞋
I never gave her the slightest provocation.
我根本没去惹她
The slippers came at my head before I uttered a word.
我话还没讲拖鞋就扔到我头上了
She used the most disgraceful language. I was shocked! I don't understand.
她说了很多难听话，太令我吃惊了，搞不懂
We always gave her every consideration. She admitted it.
我们一向待她不错，她自己也承认的
I'm dashed!
我给弄糊涂了！
Pickering, for God's sake, stop being dashed and do something!
皮克林，不要装糊涂，快想办法！
Phone the police. What are they there for?
快报警。警察是干什么吃的？
You can't give Eliza's name to the police...
你不能把伊莱莎的名字报给警察…
...as if she were a thief or a lost umbrella.
…好象当她是小偷或是一把丢掉的伞
But why not? I want to find the girl.
为什么不？我要找回这姑娘
She belongs to me. I paid five pounds for her.
她是我的。我为她付了五英镑
Quite right. Hello. Scotland Yard, please?
好吧。喂，请接苏格兰场好吗？
Get me some coffee, would you please?
请给我拿咖啡来，好吗？
Scotland Yard?
苏格兰场吗？
This is Colonel Pickering speaking.
我是皮克林上校
27A Wimpole Street.
温坡街27A
I want to report a missing person.
我这里有人失踪
Miss Eliza Doolittle.
伊莱莎杜利特小姐
About 21 .
大概21岁
I should say about 5 foot 7.
我想大概57
Her eyes? Let me think now. Her eyes....
她的眼睛？让我先想想。她的眼睛是…
-Brown.
-褐色的。 -褐色的
Her hair? Good Lord. Sort of a nondescript neutral sort of--
她的头发？老天。好象是一种什么…
Brown, brown, brown!
褐色，褐色，褐色！
You heard what he said? Brown, brown, brown, yes.
你听到他说的了吧？褐色，是的
No. This is her residence. 27A--
不，这是她的住处。27A―
Yes, about between 3:00 and 4:00 this morning, I understand.
是的，我想大概今早三四点钟
No.... She's no relation, no.
不…她没什么亲戚，不
Well, let's call her a good friend, shall we?
嗯，我们可以说是好朋友，是吧？
I beg your pardon?
你说什么？
Listen to me, I don't like the tenor of that question.
你听着，你问话的口气不对
What the girl does here is our affair.
这姑娘在这里做什么是我们的事情
Your affair is to get her back so she can continue doing it.
你们的事情就是把她找到送回来
Well, I'm dashed!
嗯，我真给弄糊涂了！
'"What in heaven could have prompted her to go?
“到底她是为什么要走？
'"After such a triumph at the ball
“舞会上她获得如此成功
'"What could have depressed her?
“会是什么让她不开心？
'"What could have possessed her? I cannot understand the wretch at all'"
“她心里在想什么？我一点都弄不明白”
Higgins, I have an old school chum at the Home Office. Perhaps he could help.
希金斯，我有个老同学在内政部，也许他能帮忙
Think I'll give him a ring.
我想可以给他打个电话
Whitehall: 7244, please.
请接白厅：7244 Whitehall: 7244, please.
'"Women are irrational That's all there is to that
“女人没有理性，就是这么回事
'"Their heads are full of Cotton, hay and rags
“她们头脑里大概尽是棉絮稻草布头
'"They're nothing but exasperating lrritating, vacillating, calculating
“只知道生气发火犹犹豫豫斤斤计较
'"Agitating, maddening And infuriating hags'"
“又小肚鸡肠又疯疯癫癫又朝三暮四
I want to speak to Mr. Brewster Budgin, please.
请找一下布鲁斯特巴金先生
Yes, I'll wait.
好的，我在等
Pickering, why can't a woman be more like a man?
皮克林，为什么女人就不能象个男人
I beg your pardon?
你说什么？
Yes, why can't a woman be more like a man?
对，为什么女人就不能象个男人？
'"Men are so honest, so thoroughly square
“男人是如此诚实可信，如此正直无欺
'"Eternally noble, historically fair
“象真理一样高尚，象历史一样公平
'"Who, when you win Will always give your back a pat?
“如果你获得成功他一定会赞扬你
'"Why can't a woman be like that?
“为什么女人就不能象那样？
'"Why does every one do What the others do?
“为什么怎么事都学别人的样子？
'"Can't a woman learn to use her head?
“为什么女人不去用她的脑子？
'"Why do they do everything Their mothers do?
“为什么母亲怎么做她们就怎么做？
'"Why don't they grow up Well, like their father instead?
“为他们她们不能学学她们的父亲？
'"Why can't a woman take after a man?
“为什么女人不能学学男人？
'"Men are so pleasant, so easy to please
“男人多么随和，随遇而安
'"Whenever you're with them You're always at ease
“和他们在一起总觉得轻松
'"Would you be slighted lf I didn't speak for hours?
“如果我长时间沉默你会不会抱怨？
'"Would you be livid lf I had a drink or two?
“如果我喝两杯酒你会不会沉下脸？
'"Would you be wounded lf I never sent you flowers?
“如果我不送花给你你会不会生气？
'"Well, why can't a woman be like you?
“那为什么女人不能象你一样？
'"One man in a million may shout a bit
“一百万男人站一起也不会太吵闹
'"Now and then There's one with slight defects
“偶尔他们可能有一些小缺点
'"One perhaps whose truthfulness You doubt a bit
“有的人也许会让你难以信任
'"But by and large We are a marvelous sex
“但基本上我们是非凡的性别
'"Why can't a woman take after a man?
“为什么女人不能学学男人？
'"Cause men are so friendly Good-natured and kind
“因为男人是如此友好亲切
'"A better companion You never will find
“哪里能有比他们更好伙伴
'"lf I were hours late for dinner Would you bellow?
“如果我晚点回来吃饭你会唠叨吗？
'"lf I forgot your silly birthday Would you fuss?
“如果我忘记你的生日你会发火吗？
'"Would you complain lf I took out another fellow?
“如果我带别人出去你会抱怨吗？
'"Well, why can't a woman be like us?'"
“那为什么女人不能象我们一样？
Is Mr. Brewster Budgin there?
布斯特柏金在吗？
Bruzzie, you'll never guess who this is.
小布，你猜不出我是谁吧
You're quite right, it is. Good heavens. By George, what a memory.
你说对了，是。老天，你记性真好
How are you, Bruzzie? Nice to hear your voice.
你好吗，小布？很高兴又听到你的声音
What? You don't say. Has it really been 30 years, Bruzzie?
什么？不会吧，真的已经30年了，小布？
Right. Yes, oceans of water.
好，没错，沧海桑田啊
Listen, Bruzzie, I'll tell you why I rang up.
听我说，小布，我打电话给你有事情
Something rather unpleasant has happened. Could I come and see you?
发生了一件不太愉快的事，我能来看看你吗？
I could, yes. Now, straight away?
可以，好。现在，马上？
Right. Good. Thank you.
好，好。谢谢
Goodbye, Bruzzie. Thank you very much.
再见，小布。非常感谢
Mrs. Pearce, I'm going along to the Home Office.
佩思太太，我要去内政部
I do hope you find her, Colonel Pickering.
我希望你找到她，皮克林上校
Mr. Higgins will miss her.
希金斯先生会想念她的
Mr. Higgins will miss her, eh? Blast Mr. Higgins, I'll miss her!
希金斯先生会想念她？嘿，我更想念她！
-Mrs. Pearce? -Yes, sir.
-佩斯太太？ -先生
Where's the Colonel?
上校哪儿去了？
He's gone to the Home Office, sir.
他去内政部了，先生
There you are. I'm disturbed and he runs for help. Now there's a good fellow.
你看。我有烦心事他去为我奔忙。多好的人
Mrs. Pearce, you're a woman.
佩斯太太，你也是女人
'"Why can't a woman be more like a man?
“为什么女人不能像男人一样？
'"Men are so decent Such regular chaps
“男人是如此正派如此穿着得体
'"Ready to help you Through any mishaps
“总会帮你战胜任何困难
'"Ready to buck you up Whenever you are glum
“总会助你走出郁闷时刻
'"Why can't a woman be a chum?
“为何女人就不能成为知已？
'"Why is thinking Something women never do?
“为什么女人永远不会思考？
'"And why is logic never even tried?
“为什么她们不能条理分明？
'"Straightening up their hair ls all they ever do
“只知道如何梳理她们的头发
'"Why don't they straighten up The mess that's inside?
“为什么就不能梳理一下思想？
'"Why can't a woman behave like a man?
“为什么女人就不能学学男人？
'"lf I was a woman Who'd been to a ball
“如果我是个女人去参加舞会
'"Been hailed as a princess By one and by all
“得到所有人像公主般的对待
'"Would I start weeping Like a bathtub overflowing?
“难道我会哭得像水溢出浴缸？
'"Or carry on as if my home were in a tree?
“或者我会像鸟儿一样举止反常？
'"Would I run off And never tell me where I'm going?
“难道我会不说清楚就匆忙跑掉？
'"Why can't a woman be like me?'"
“为什么女人就不能象我一样？”
You mean that after you'd done this wonderful thing for them...
你说你为他们做了这么多了不起的事…
...without making a mistake...
…没出过一点错…
...they just sat there and never said a word?
…他们却坐在那里一句表示都没有？
Never petted you, or admired you, or told you how splendid you'd been?
没有夸奖，也没有赞扬？
Not a word.
一个字都没提
They just congratulated each other on how marvelous they'd been.
他们只顾相互祝贺相互吹捧
The next moment, how glad they were it was all over...
然后又说他们很高兴一切都结束了…
...and what a bore it had all been.
…说他们完成的是一项壮举
This is appalling. I should not have thrown my slippers at him.
真难以置信，我可不会向他扔拖鞋
I should have thrown the fire irons.
我会向他扔烙铁
Who's that?
是谁？
Henry. I knew it wouldn't be too long.
亨利。我知道不用等很久
Now, remember...
现在，记住…
...you not only danced with a prince last night, you behaved like a princess.
…昨晚你不只是与王子共舞，你表现得象公主
Mother, the most confounded thing.... Do you--
母亲，这事情太奇怪了…你…
You!
你！
Good afternoon, Professor Higgins. Are you quite well?
下午好，希金斯教授，你还好吗？
Of course you are. You are never ill. Would you care for some tea?
当然好。你从来不生病。你要喝茶吗？
Don't you dare try that game on me. I taught it to you.
别和我玩这种把戏。都是我教你的
Get up, come home and stop being a fool.
快跟我回家，别犯傻了
You've caused me enough trouble.
你给我惹够多麻烦了
Very nicely put indeed, Henry. No woman could resist such an invitation.
很好，亨利。没有女人能拒绝这样的邀请
How did this baggage get here?
这小东西怎么会来这里？
Eliza came to see me this morning and I was delighted to have her.
伊莱莎一早就来看我，我很高兴她来
If you don't promise to behave yourself I'll ask you to leave.
如果你再不规矩，我就要请你离开
I'm to put on my Sunday manners for this...
我好心好意地…
...thing that I created out of the squashed cabbage leaves of Covent Garden?
…将她从乱哄哄的菜市场带出来
That's precisely what I mean.
就是这样
I'll see her damned first.
我要请她先滚
However did you learn good manners with my son around?
在我儿子那儿你怎么能学好礼仪？
It was very difficult. I should never have known how ladies and gentlemen behave...
很难啊。在那儿我可能永远都学不会淑女的礼仪…
...if it hadn't been for Colonel Pickering.
…幸亏在那儿还有皮克林上校
He showed me that he felt and thought about me...
他对待我的态度和言行…
...as if I were something better than a common flower girl.
…不象是对待一个普通卖花女
You see, Mrs. Higgins, apart from the things one can pick up...
你看，希金斯太太，礼仪可以学到…
...the difference between a lady and a flower girl isn't how she behaves...
…淑女和卖花女的差别是在于她的行为…
...but how she is treated.
…而在于人们对待她的态度
I'll always be a flower girl to Professor Higgins...
对教授来说我永远是个卖花女…
...because he always treats me as a flower girl and always will.
…因为他永远把我当卖花女一样对待
I'll always be a lady to Colonel Pickering...
对皮克林上校来说我永远是个淑女…
...because he always treats me as a lady and always will.
…因为他永远把我当淑女一样对待
Henry, don't grind your teeth.
亨利，别咬牙切齿的
The bishop is here. Shall I show him into the garden?
主教来了，请他到花园来吗？
The bishop and the professor? Good heavens, no!
主教和教授呆在一起，老天，不行！
I should be excommunicated.
我会被开除教籍的
I'll see him in the library.
我到书房去见他
Eliza, if my son starts breaking up things...
伊莱莎，要是我儿子敢欺负你…
...l give you full permission to have him evicted.
…请你替我把她赶出去
Henry, I suggest you stick to two subjects: the weather and your health.
亨利，我建议你们谈两个话题：天气和健康
You've had a bit of your own back, as you say.
你找到了一点所谓的自尊
Have you had enough and will you be reasonable or do you want any more?
闹够后可以开始讲讲道理了吧？
You want me back to pick up your slippers...
你要我回去帮你捡拖鞋…
...and put up with your tempers and fetch and carry for you.
…继续忍受你的怪脾气
I didn't say I wanted you back at all.
我根本没说要你回去
Then what are we talking about?
那我们还有什么可说的？
Well, about you, not about me.
是说你，不是说我
If you come back you'll be treated as you always have.
如果你回来还会得到原来一样的对待
I can't change my nature or my manners.
我不可能改变我的性格和态度
My manners are exactly the same as Colonel Pickering's.
我的态度和皮克林上校是完全一样的
That's not true. He treats a flower girl as if she were a duchess.
不是的。他对待卖花女就象对待公爵夫人
I treat a duchess as if she was a flower girl.
我对待公爵夫人就象对待卖花女
I see. The same to everybody.
明白了，对谁都一样
The great secret is not a question of good manners...
这不是什么好态度的问题
...or bad manners or any particular sort of manner...
…也不是坏态度或任何一种态度的问题…
...but having the same manner for all human souls.
…而是对所有人都一视同仁的态度
The question is not whether I treat you rudely...
问题不在于我对你态度不好…
...but whether you've ever heard me treat anyone else better.
…我对你的态度和对别人是一样的
I don't care how you treat me.
我才不在乎你怎么对待我
I don't mind your swearing at me. I shouldn't mind a black eye.
我不在乎你骂我，也不在乎你的冷眼
I've had one before this. But I won't be passed over!
我以前也习惯了。但不能丢下我不管！
Get out of my way, for I won't stop for you.
别缠着我，我还有事要忙
You talk about me as though I was a motorbus.
你说得我好象是一辆公共汽车
So you are a motorbus. All bounce and go and no consideration for anybody.
你就是辆公共汽车。从不管是谁在上下车
But I can get along without you. Don't you think I can't!
没有你我照样能生活，别以为我不行！
I know you can. I told you, you could.
我知道你行。我说过你行
You've never wondered, I suppose, whether...
我想你从来没有想过…
...whether I could get along without you?
…没有你我也照样生活？
Don't you try to get around me. You'll have to.
你不要搞错了，是你自找的
So I can, without you or any soul on earth.
当然，没有你或任何其他人
I shall miss you, Eliza. I've learned something from your idiotic notions.
我会想你，伊莱莎。你的想法也让我有所收获
I confess that humbly and gratefully.
我得真心承认这一点
Well, you have my voice on your gramophone.
你的留声机里有我的声音
When you feel lonely without me you can turn it on. It has no feelings to hurt.
你无聊时可以听一听，它没感情不怕受伤害
Well, I can't turn your soul on.
你的灵魂是留不下的
You are a devil!
你真是个魔鬼！
You can twist the heart in a girl just as easily...
你伤一个姑娘的心…
...as some can twist her arms to hurt her.
…就像扭伤他的手臂一样容易
What am I to come back for?
我回去能做什么？
For the fun of it. That's why I took you on.
能快乐地生活，我请你回去
You may throw me out tomorrow if I don't do everything you want.
如果我不听你话明天又会被赶出来
Yes. And you may walk out tomorrow
对，如果我不听你话你明天就可以走
And live with my father?
去和我父亲住一起？
Yes, or sell flowers. Would you rather marry Pickering?
对，或去花店。要么嫁给皮克林？
I wouldn't marry you if you asked me and you're nearer my age then what he is.
我肯定不会嫁你，就算你年纪轻比他
-Than he is. -I'll talk as I like, you're not my teacher.
-比他年纪轻。 -我爱怎么说就怎么说，不用你教
That's not what I want and don't you think it is.
我不想这么做，你别乱想
I've always had chaps enough wanting me that way.
追我的人多了去了
Freddy Hill writes me twice and three times a day. Sheets and sheets.
弗雷迪希尔一天写好几封好几页的信给我
In short, you want me to be as infatuated about you as he is, is that it?
这么说，你是要我也象他一样对你痴情
No, I don't. That's not the sort of feeling I want from you.
不是。我不是要你这样对待我
I want a little kindness.
我只求你稍微亲切一点
I know I'm a common, ignorant girl, and you're a book-learned gentleman...
我是个无知的普通女孩，你是个博学的绅士
...but I'm not dirt under your feet.
…可我也不是你脚下的尘土
What I done...what I did was not for the taxis and the dresses...
我所做的…不是为了能坐车和穿好衣服…
...but because we were pleasant together and I come to...came...
…而是为了能愉快相处，我来是…
...to care for you.
…因为在乎你
Not to want you to make love to me...
不是想要你向我求爱…
...and not forgetting the difference between us, but...
…不是忘记了我们之间的悬殊，而是…
...more friendly like.
…渴望友谊
Well, of course. That's how I feel.
嗯，当然，我也这样想
And how Pickering feels. Eliza, you're a fool!
皮克林也这样想，伊莱莎你真傻
That's not the proper answer.
我要的不是这个答案
It's the only answer till you stop being an idiot.
你理智一点，这是唯一正确的答案
To be a lady, you must stop feeling neglected...
要做个淑女，你不能总感觉被忽视…
...if men don't spend half their time sniveling over you...
…如果人们不是总花一半时间恭维你…
...and the other half giving you black eyes.
…另一半时间又冷淡你…
You find me cold, unfeeling, selfish, don't you?
你觉得我冷淡、没感情、自私，是吗？
Off with you to the sort of people you like.
你可以去找到你喜欢的人
Marry a sentimental hog with lots of money...
去嫁一个有钱有感情的家伙…
...and thick lips to kiss you, and thick boots to kick you.
…有空亲你，有空揍你
If you can't appreciate what you have, then get what you can appreciate.
既然你不喜欢你所拥有的，那就另找你喜欢的
I can't talk to you. You always turn everything against me.
我不和你讲，说来说去都是我不对
I'm always in the wrong.
我永远是错的
Don't be too sure you have me under your feet...
别以为你肯定比我强…
...to be trampled on and talked down.
…容易欺骗容易说服
I'll marry Freddy, I will, as soon as I'm able to support him.
我要嫁给弗雷迪，我还有能力供养他
The poor devil who couldn't get a job as an errand boy...
那伙做连跑堂的差事都不能胜任…
...even if he had the guts to try?
…即使他有勇气去做？
Don't you understand? I have made you a consort for a king!
你不明白？我把你教得够资格嫁国王！
Freddy loves me. That makes him king enough for me.
弗雷迪爱我。他够资格做我的国王
I don't want him to work. He wasn't brought up to do it as I was.
我不要他去工作。他不象我那样习惯干活
I'll go and be a teacher.
我可以去当教师
What'll you teach, in heaven's name?
你能教什么？
What you taught me. I'll teach phonetics.
你教我的东西。我去教语音学
I'll offer myself as an assistant to that brilliant Hungarian.
我可以自荐当那了不起的匈牙利人的助手
What, that imposter? That humbug? That toadying ignoramus?
什么，那个只会溜须拍马不学无术的骗子
Teach him my methods, my discoveries?
用我发明的教学方法？
You take one step in that direction, I'll wring your neck!
你敢这么干，我扭断你的脖子！
Wring away! What do I care? I knew you'd strike me one day.
扭啊！我怕你吗？早知道你想这么干
That's done you, 'Enry 'lggins, it 'as.
没脾气了吧，亨利希金斯
Now, I don't care for your bullyin' an' your big talk.
现在我不吃你这一套了
'"What a fool I was
“我曾经是多么的傻
'"What a dominated fool
“多么的糊涂
'"To think you were the earth and sky
“以为你就是天和地
'"What a fool I was
“我曾经是多么的傻
'"What an addle-pated fool
“多么的糊涂
'"What a mutton-headed dolt was I
“曾经是多么的死脑筋
'"No, my reverberating friend
“不，爱顶嘴的朋友
'"You are not the beginning and the end'"
“你并不是世上的一切”
You impudent hussy!
你这放肆的泼妇！
There's not an idea in your head or a word in your mouth that I haven't put there.
你头脑里的思想和口中的词汇都是我给予你的
'"There'll be spring every year without you
“没有你每年春天还会来
'"England still will be here without you
“没有你英格兰还会存在
'"There'll be fruit on the tree And a shore by the sea
“树上照样结果，海水照样拍打海岸
'"There'll be crumpets and tea without you
“没有你点心和茶水还会存在
'"Art and music will thrive without you
“没有你艺术和音乐还会兴盛
'"Somehow Keats will survive without you
“没有你诗人们还会生活下去
'"And there still will be rain On that plain down in Spain
“西班牙的雨照样下在平原
'"Even that will remain without you
“没有你它们都不会受影响
'"l can do...
“我也一样…
'"...without you
“…没有你
'"You, dear friend
“亲爱的朋友
'"Who talk so well
“你这么会说话
'"You can go to
“你可以去
'"Hartford, Hereford and Hampshire
“哈特福德、赫福德和汉普郡
'"They can still rule the land without you
“没有你国家政府照样运转
'"Windsor Castle will stand without you
“没有你温莎堡照样矗立
'"And without much ado We can all muddle through
”不用慌乱我们照样能生活
'"Without you! '"
“没有你！”
You brazen hussy!
你这厚脸皮的泼妇！
'"Without your pulling it the tide comes in
“没有你潮水还是会起落
'"Without your twirling it the earth can spin
“没有你地球还是会旋转
'"Without your pushing them the clouds roll by
没有你云彩还是会飘浮
'"lf they can do without you, Ducky, So can I
“没有你它们都不会受影响，我也一样
'"l shall not feel alone without you
“没有你我不会感到孤独
'"l can stand on my own without you
“没有你我能够自谋生路
'"So go back in your shell I can do bloody well--'"
“你爬回乌龟壳去吧，我能自己生活――”
'"By George, I really did it I did it, I did it
“老天，我做到了，我做到了”
'"l said I'd make a woman and indeed I did
“我说我要创造一个女人，我说到做到
'"l knew that I could do it I knew it, I knew it
“我知道我能做到，我知道，我知道
'"l said I'd make a woman and succeed I did'"
“我说我要创造一个女人，我成功了”
Eliza, you're magnificent.
伊莱莎，你真了不起
Five minutes ago you were a millstone around my neck...
五分钟前你还是我的负累…
...and now you're a tower of strength.
…现在你却象矗立的高塔
A consort battleship.
强大得象艘战列舰
I like you this way.
我喜欢你这样子
Goodbye, Professor Higgins. You shall not be seeing me again.
再见，希金斯教授，你不会再见到我了
Mother!
母亲！
What is it, Henry? What's happened?
怎么了，亨利？怎么了？
She's gone.
她走了
Well, of course, dear. What did you expect?
当然啦，亲爱的。你以为会怎样？
What am I to do?
我怎么办？
Do without, I suppose.
照旧呗
And so I shall.
我会的
If the Higgins' oxygen burns up her little lungs...
如果我给她的东西她不喜欢
...let her seek some stuffiness that suits her.
…让她自已去找合适的
She's an owl sickened by a few days of my sunshine.
就象阳光不适合夜猫子
Let her go. I can do without her.
随她去吧。没有她我能行
I can do without anyone. I have my own soul!
没有谁我都能行。我有我自己的灵魂！
My own spark of divine fire!
我自己神圣的火焰！
Bravo, Eliza.
干得好，伊莱莎
'"Damn, damn, damn, damn
“该死，该死，该死，该死
'"l've grown accustomed to her face
“我已习惯了她的样子
'"She almost makes the day begin
“是她让新一天开始
'"l've grown accustomed to the tune That she whistles night and noon
“我已习惯了她从早到晚了口哨声
'"Her smiles, her frowns Her ups, her downs
“她的微笑蹙眉高兴悲伤
'"Are second nature to me now
“成为我天性的一部分
'"Like breathing out and breathing in
“就象呼气与吸气
'"l was serenely independent and content Before we met
“见面之前我独立自足
'"Surely I could always be that way again
“现在我当然也能回到从前
'"And yet I've grown Accustomed to her looks
“但我已习惯了她的样子
'"Accustomed to her voice
“习惯了她的声音
'"Accustomed to her face'"
“习惯了她的脸庞”
Marry Freddy.
嫁给弗雷迪
What an infantile idea. What a heartless, wicked, brainless thing to do.
多么幼稚的想法。多么可恶无情的做法
But she'll regret it. She'll regret it.
她一定会后悔，他一定会后悔
It's doomed before they even take the vow!
不用起誓就注定完蛋
'"l can see her now Mrs. Freddy Eynsford-Hill
“我可以想象弗雷迪恩福希尔太太
'"ln a wretched little flat above a store
“栖身小商店楼上的小阁楼
'"l can see her now, not a penny in the till
“我可以想象她会一文不名
'"And a bill collector beating at the door
“债主们上门催帐
'"She'll try to teach the things I taught her
“她想教我教她的学问
'"And end up selling flowers instead
“结果还是只能去卖花
'"Begging for her bread and water
“为了生计而乞讨
'"While her husband has his breakfast in bed
“而她先生却躺在床上吃早餐
'"ln a year or so when she's prematurely gray
“不用一年她就早生华发
'"And the blossom in her cheek has turned to chalk
“脸颊上的红晕会变惨白
'"She'll come home and lo he'll have upped and run away
“她回到家，发现他无影无踪
'"With a social-climbing heiress from New York
“已跟一个纽约来的女大款私奔
'"Poor Eliza
“可怜的伊莱莎
'"How simply frightful
“多么可怕的后果
'"How humiliating
“多么丢人的结局
'"How delightful
“多么解气
'"How poignant it will be On that inevitable night
“那一夜会是多么戏剧性
'"When she hammers on my door ln tears and rags
“当她哭着来叩我的家门
'"Miserable and lonely Repentant and contrite
“可怜、孤独又懊悔
'"Will I take her in Or hurl her to the wolves?
“我该让她进来还是拿她喂狼？
'"Give her kindness Or the treatment she deserves?
“以德报怨还是给她应得的惩罚？
'"Will I take her back Or throw the baggage out?
“我该收留她还是赶她出门？
'"Well, I'm a most forgiving man
“嗯，我是个最宽容的人
'"The sort who never could, ever would
“从不愿意记仇
'"Take a position and staunchly never budge
“立场坚定不改
'"A most forgiving man
“一个最宽容的人
'"But I shall never take her back
“但我绝不会再收留她
'"lf she were crawling on her knees
“就算她跪下来求我
'"Let her promise to atone Let her shiver, let her moan
“让她承诺赔罪、让她战抖哀号
'"l'll slam the door And let the hellcat freeze'"
“我会关上门，随这泼妇冻死”
Marry Freddy.
嫁给弗雷迪
'"But I'm so used to hear her say
“但我已习惯她
'"'Good morning' every day
“每天说‘早安’
'"Her joys, her woes
“她的快乐，她的悲伤
'"Her highs, her lows
“她的欢喜，她的苦恼
'"Are second nature to me now
“已成为我天性的一部分
'"Like breathing out and breathing in
“就象呼气与吸气
'"l'm very grateful she's a woman And so easy to forget
“我庆幸她是个女人，容易忘记
'"Rather like a habit one can always break
“就象轻易能改掉的习惯
'"And yet I've grown Accustomed to the trace
“但我已习惯了
'"Of something in the air
“她存在的气息
'"Accustomed to her face'"
“习惯了她的脸庞”
Oh, we are proud. He ain't above givin' lessons, not 'im. I 'eard 'im say so.
我们都很骄傲。他不教课，我听他这么说的
I ain't come here to ask for any compliment...
我来不是要听客气话…
...and if my money's not good enough, I can go elsewhere.
…要是我的钱不够，我就去别处
Good enough for what?
不够什么？
Good enough for you. Now you know, don't ya?
够付你学费。你听明白了吗？
I'm come to 'ave lessons. And to pay for 'em, too...
我是来学习的，还会付学费…
...make no mistake.
…别搞错了
What do you want, my girl?
你想做什么，姑娘？
I want to be a lady in a flow'r shop, 'stead o' sellin'...
我想做个花店女店员，而不是…
...at the corner of Tottenham Court Road.
…而不是在街角卖花
But they won't take me unless I can talk more genteel. He said he could teach me.
但他们不要，除非我说话好听。他说他能教我
Well, 'ere I am ready to pay. Not askin' any favor, and he treats me as if I was dirt.
我愿意付钱。不要求其他，他却待我象尘土
I know what lessons cost as well as you do and I'm ready to pay.
我知道你的课程的收费，我愿意付钱
I won't give more than a shillin'. Take it or leave it.
我最多出一先令，要不要随你
It's almost irresistible. She's so deliciously low.
真是难以拒绝。她这么卑微
So horribly dirty. I'll take it.
这么肮脏。我愿意接受
I'll make a duchess of this draggle-tailed guttersnipe.
我会将这个邋遢的穷姑娘变成公爵夫人
I washed my face and 'ands before I come, I did.
我来以前刚洗过脸和手，真的
Where the devil are my slippers?
我的拖鞋到底哪去了？